<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the planting of the Massachusetts Colony anno 1628 with the Lords signal presence the first thirty years : also a caution from New-Englands apostle, the great Cotton, how to escape the calamity which might befall them or their posterity, and confirmed by the evangelist Norton, with prognosticks from the famous Dr. Owen concerning the fate of these churches, and animadversions upon the anger of God in sending of evil angels among us / published by Old Planters, the authors of the Old mens tears.</title>
            <author>Scottow, Joshua, 1618-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33724</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13553158</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13553158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58837)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1557:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the planting of the Massachusetts Colony anno 1628 with the Lords signal presence the first thirty years : also a caution from New-Englands apostle, the great Cotton, how to escape the calamity which might befall them or their posterity, and confirmed by the evangelist Norton, with prognosticks from the famous Dr. Owen concerning the fate of these churches, and animadversions upon the anger of God in sending of evil angels among us / published by Old Planters, the authors of the Old mens tears.</title>
                  <author>Scottow, Joshua, 1618-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 76, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Benjamin Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A funeral elegy upon the death of the truly reverend Mr. John Cotton" signed John Norton (p. 75-[76])</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped and stained with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Massachusetts --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE Of The <hi>Planting</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> COLONY Anno 1628. With the LORDS Signal Preſence the Firſt Thirty YEARS.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Caution from <hi>New-Englands <hi>APOSTLE,</hi>
               </hi> the GREAT COTTON, How to Eſcape the Calamity, which might Befall them or their <hi>POSTERITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Confirmed by the <hi>EVANGELIST</hi> NORTON With Prognoſticks from the <hi>FAMOUS Dr.</hi> OWEN.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Fate of theſe Churches, and Animadverſions upon the Anger of God, in ſending of Evil Angels among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Old Planters, the Authors of the Old Mens Tears</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 78.2.3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl> I will utter dark ſayings of Old. Which we have heard and known and our Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers have told us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl> Thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand ye in the ways and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie; and ask for the old paths, where is the good way, &amp; walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein, and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſouls; but they ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will not walk therein.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſton</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi> at the ſign of the BIBLE over-againſt the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lem-A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> 160<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Honourable</hi> Simon Broadſtreet <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Late GOVERNOUR of the <hi>Maſſachuſets-Colony.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Long Experience of your being the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Surviving Antiquary of us <hi>Nov-Angle</hi> the Prime Secretary and Regiſter of our civil a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſacred Records, and the Bifronted <hi>Janus</hi> who ſaw t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cloſure</hi> of the Old, and the Overture of this Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Albion</hi> World. One who in your <hi>Juveni</hi> strength ingaged your All, to Raiſe and Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> up the Arduous &amp; Hazzardous Structure, of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then deſpiſed and deſpicable Fabrique; ſo as its o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſervers ſaid of it, what will theſe Feeble me Build, if a <hi>Fox</hi> go up, he ſhall even break dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſtone-wall: of which themſelves, and all is Spectators muſt now ſay, <hi>Lo, what hath Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Great <hi>GOD</hi> did then ſelect and adap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Your Perſon, and Enrowle your Name among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nurſing Fathers of this his <hi>Out caſt Sion,</hi> whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Names are imbalmed to Eternity: that you have through nine hard Apprentiſhips, of above ſixty years durance, in the ſervice of your Generation, and faithful diſcharge of that truſt for ſo long a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:100210:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as hath Rendred you a <hi>MOOT-MAN,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be dignified with the highest Honour, this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> were capable to confer,</p>
            <p>Whither ſhould this narrow Narrative go, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake its addreſs for Patronage, and Avowry of its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erity, but to Your Honours feet, there to Prostrate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſubmit it ſelf to the touch and teſt of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an Stone thereof, its ſubstance being extracted out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Records, and the reſt founded upon the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers certaine knowledge and obſervation.</p>
            <p>As for the Cenſure of the whole or part, to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elyrious dotage of <hi>Bis Puerile</hi> and Superannuated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rains, let ſuch pleaſe to ſatisfy themſelves with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir own Speculations.</p>
            <p>But for Your Venerable Self, that the Ancient of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays, and the God of the Spirits of all fleſh, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſe to renew Your Age as the Eagles, ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u may be Our <hi>New-England Neſtor,</hi> that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cays of Your outward may be made up, by recruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> freſh Anointing from above upon Your Inner man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at Your Dayes may be prolonged, to remain in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſt of thoſe who actually are, <hi>Our Fathers, Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>athers, the Chariots of our Iſrael; and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſemen thereof,</hi> and until you are become a full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pe Sheaf, fit to be ſafely laid up in Your Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Maſters Garner. <hi>Is the Daily Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours Humble, and Obliged Servant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100210:3"/>
            <head>A NARRATIVE Of the Planting of the Maſſachuſets-Colony &amp;c</head>
            <p>THE Late Series of Divine Diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations tending not only to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſſolving of the Cemer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Subverting of the Baſis of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fabrick which the Wonder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Worker hath here ſo ſtupendiouſly erected; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Cropping off their Branches, but to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Rooting up of the tender Plant, which the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, here ſo graciouſly hath Plante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath put ſome of the Old Relict Plante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>ſmiting on our thighs,</hi> and ſerious co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of what provoking evils we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> committed, and what ſpecial ſins, God no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would bring to our Remembrance, whereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we have ſo highly diſpleaſed our Benig
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100210:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l, and Gracious Father, thus tremenduouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat us: the Aſpect of Providence ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y varying, from what formerly it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt to be, puts us into an amuſing amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt. And being in this perple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, of Diſtracting thoughts of heart, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> darted into our Meditations, a Caution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich above Eight Septenaries of Years paſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me from the firſt Seraphical Doctor of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cton</hi> Church. Mr <hi>John Cotton,</hi> whoſe name in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urches is as Ointment powred forth, and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> word of his ſucceſſor may paſs for Current, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was the greateſt Luminary in our <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d Orbs,</hi> and a great <hi>Prophet,</hi> and the truth is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt intelligent of thoſe times took them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th for no leſs; he in his funeral <hi>Elegy</hi> upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> death gave him both theſe ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nting upon Gods Magnifying him in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſs, not only in the ſight of this <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great part of the diſcerning world, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g up a Caeleſtial Flambeau in the Starry Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, whither a Signal Minatory or Monitory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t may be both) the next age will better know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>directly followed the Reer of the Pleiades, the Riſing Progreſs and ſetting of the Seven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ars, as if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had ſteer'd their Courſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt ſtrict obſervers took notice of: he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mſelf on his death bed, being Informed of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>plyed, that it did portend to the ſtate of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurches: this Comet appeared not only in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne of his ſickneſs, but until his interment, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100210:4"/>then diſappeared, thereby Performing the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable Reſpects of thoſe Stately Obſequi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which are only due, and not done to any, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Perſons of greateſt honour, as to the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Notables, and Scavants of the times, had the but a ſhadow of the leaſt Pretext to ſuch thing, befaln the Ignation, <hi>Peter Cotton,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Famed Jeſuite, in his life or death, it had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beyond diſpute that his Preference in their R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke, or Saints Calender had been befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Loyala</hi> their firſt Founder.</p>
            <p>This Worthy man of God's ſucceſſor Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end <hi>Norton</hi> thus verſified of him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>This <hi>Prophet's</hi> dead now muſt in's Doctrine ſpeak</l>
               <l>This <hi>Comet</hi> ſaith, Elſe Must New-England break</l>
            </q>
            <p>How near <hi>New-England</hi> now is to its brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the All-knowing One only knows; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the muteneſs of this Prophets Doctrine, is wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all ſolemnity and ſadneſs of Soul to be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
            <p>This Venerable Seer, whoſe method was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> go through the Books of Scripture, he Entre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon, and had in his Miniſterial Courſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both <hi>Boſtons</hi> been (lengthened our to little le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then forty years) went through near the whole Bible, he was then upon <hi>Acts</hi> 7. concerning <hi>Stephens</hi> Diſcourſe before the Council, about the Hiſtory of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Church in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, taking up the Tabernacle of <hi>Molock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100210:5"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the Star of their God Remphan;</hi> Figures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich they made to Worſhip: whereupon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods Threatning immediately followed. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will carry you away beyond Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilon.</hi> Shewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at this provocation was ſo great, as God then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reatned them with the <hi>Babylorian</hi> Captivity, which befel their Poſterity divers hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears after; he notified the time when, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace where, and the perſons threatned were Gods Covenant People; whence he obſerved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Gods Covenant People, or their Children, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight in their firſt beginnings be loft to do ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bings, as might bring a future grievous Calamity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſhewed as this people being Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id thus in their March through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> not many years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter their Departure from <hi>Egypt,</hi> their <hi>Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bondage;</hi> So might any other Covenant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople be left to do.</p>
            <p>In the Application of this Doctrine, he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſiſted with that Preſence of Spirit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſed it upon his Auditors with its Divine Authority, that as Goads and Nails, it Entred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom that Maſter of the Aſſembly, and was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtned from the one Shepheard. Such was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Attention, and its Efficacy upon the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, (words from the heart entred into their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts) ſo as upon Repitition of the Sermon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> home, they coming warmed with its hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100210:5"/>heat, concluded their <hi>John</hi> was in the Spirit <hi>that Lords Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Prophet is Dead, <hi>and our Fathers where are they?</hi> Yet the words then ſpoken, left ſuch a Convincing Impreſs upon our hearts &amp; Souls as is not obliterated to this day, and in this Hour of Diſtreſs, Trouble, and Conſternation, is now revived, when as Heaven, Earth, and Hell ſeem to Conſpire to Accompliſh the Threatning then Denounced.</p>
            <p>The Great God being now upon ſearching our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Candles, ſhould put each individual ſenſible Soul, with the Candle of the Lord, to make diligent and ſincere Inquiry into the moſt inward and ſecret receſſes in the Chambers of his Imagery, yea into the cloſeſt Tills, and Cachotes of a deceitful and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked heart; and after all to Beg of him, <hi>whoſe Eyes are as a Flame of Fire,</hi> that he would Search, Try, and Know it, and that he would ſhew, and make us all to know every winding, and wicked way, <hi>and lead in the way Everlaſting;</hi> that he who <hi>is holy in all his Ways, and righteous in all his Works,</hi> the great Revealer of Secrets, would take off the Veil, which hides the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> in our Souls, that there may be a clear diſcovery of the <hi>Troubler of our Iſrael,</hi> the Inward Viceroy, the Judge, Jury, and Witneſs within us, their Verdict and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſſing againſt us: God who is greater than our Conſcience will condem us much more.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100210:6"/>
            <p>That we and our Fathers have Sinned, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of doubt, but whether we or our Fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the meritorious and procuring cauſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat we now are groaning under, is that which remains under queſtion, we hope in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſequel of this Script, as to vindicate the Equity of Gods Wayes towards our Fathers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd our ſelves, ſo in our weak meaſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince us of the Iniquity of our wayes againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord, that we ſhall ſee juſt cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our ſelves, as the procurers of all the deep Diſpleaſure we now bleed under.</p>
            <p>In order whereunto, it may be requiſite to Recollect what our Fathers have told us, and what we have ſeen; and ſhall preſent a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the unaccountable Sheaves of Divinely Beneficient Bounties granted unto our Fathers, and their graceful Returns unto the Divine Majeſty. It's great pitty before the preſent Generation paſs off the Stage of Action, that there ſhould not be a compleat Hiſtory laid up in our Archivis.</p>
            <p>It was an Ordinance of old, to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Political Birth and Growth of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it may not (we hope) be unbeſeeming us, to give a ſmall account of the Geneſis of this ſuperhumane and really Divine Creation, wrought by the admirable Architect, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf moſt Illuſtriouſly Great in the Minimes of Created Beings.</p>
            <p>This Colonies Foundation was not laid, by exhauſting the Exchequers of Princes, Peers, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100210:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords of the Realm, nor by Lotteries, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch like Contrivances of Advance, as other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations have been.</p>
            <p>It was incomparable Minute, to what its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow attain'd unto, and the rather to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, becauſe of the great oppoſition, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe of ſtrength it firſt met with, its growth muſt be aſſigned to Heavens Influence, and leſſing: It evidently proceeded from him who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ais'd up the Righteous man from the Eaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd called him to his Foot; the ſudden mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and incliner of Hearts, both infuſed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uided the inclinations and motions of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthy Patriots, with their Aſſociates, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther attended, or followed them in great meaſure, parallel to that of the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> who upon a Divine Call, left Kin: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, Country and Fathers Houſe, and went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e knew not whether, to Enjoy he knew not what, both proceeding from the ſame Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, and Inſtinct, drawn by the Magnetick Influence of the ſame Holy Spirit, and as it were by the impulſe of a ſacred Charm or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pell, as by its operation appeared, as if a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Herald, through our Nation from <hi>Barwick,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Cornwell</hi> had made Proclamation, to Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Muſter up Volunteers, to appear in <hi>New-England,</hi> for His Sacred Majeſties Service, here to attend further Orders: Such was the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay of Christ's Power,</hi> as an incredible number of Willing People, forthwith Liſted themſelves; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea many of thoſe whoſe Faces were unknown
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100210:7"/>each other; the hearts of multitudes in this Deſign reſponded, as Face to Face in Water; thus the Body of this People was animated a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with one Soul.</p>
            <p>That this Deſign was Super-humane, will be evidenced by the <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> or grand Wheel thereof. Neither Spaniſh Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, nor <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Trade of Peltry did Oil their Wheels; it was the Propagation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Piety and Religion to Poſterity; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Macedonean Call, COME OVER AND HELP US, afterward Inſtamp'd in the Seal of this Colony, the Setting up of Chriſt's Kingdom among the Heathens, in this Remo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> End of the Earch, was the main ſpring of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that which gave the Name to <hi>New-England,</hi> and at ſuch a time, when as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Herbert</hi> in his Temple Prophetically Sang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Religion Stands on Tiptoe in our Land,</l>
               <l>Ready to paſs to the <hi>American</hi> Strand.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The agency of the great God appeared, who never lets any of his works, fall for want of materials or inſtruments, he raiſed up ſuch as were fit to lead, and feed this People in this wilderneſs, ſuch were our Famous Founders we had our <hi>Moſe's,</hi> and <hi>Aaron's,</hi> our <hi>Zorobabels</hi> and <hi>Joſhua's,</hi> our <hi>Ezrah's,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Noble ſpirited perſons, fitted and called o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, raiſed up to this great ſervice, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Civil and Sacred Adminiſtration, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cure and Care of this flock in this wilderneſs.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100210:7"/>
            <p>Men of narrow ſpirits, of mean Capacities, and fortunes, had not been capable to officiate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſo great a worke, that ſuch, and ſo many Gentlemen of Ancient and Worſhipful Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, of Name and Number, of Character and Quality, ſhould Combine and Unite in ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erate and dangerous a Deſign, attended with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch inſuperable Difficulties, and Hazards, in the plucking up of their Stakes, leaving ſo pleaſant and profitable a place as their Native <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oil, parting with their Patrimonies, Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, plentiful Eſtates, and ſettlement of Houſes well Furniſhed; of Land well Stock'd, and with comfortable ways of Subſiſtence, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he firſt Planters Deſerted; and not a few did leave all their worldly hopes, to come into this Deſert, &amp; unknown Land, and ſmoaky Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, to the Society of Curſed Cannibals, (as they have proved to be) and at beſt wild Indians; what leſs then a Divine Ardour could inflame a People thus Circumſtanced to a work ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Fleſh and Blood.</p>
            <p>Infinite Wiſdom and Prudence contrived and directed this Myſterious Work of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Divine Courage and Reſolution mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, Superhumane Sedulity and Diligence-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tended it, and Angelical Swiftneſs and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>patch finiſhed it; Its Wheels ſtirr'd not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it according to the HOLY SPIRITS mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on in them; yea there was the Involution of a Wheel within a Wheel: Gods Ways were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Great Depth, and high above the Eagle or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100210:8"/>mans Cockle-ſhell is infinitely unable to Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie this Ocean.</p>
            <p>Let us Commemorate their <hi>Exodus</hi> or Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from our Nation. Theſe Prudent Under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers ſent forth their <hi>Forlorn Hope</hi> in two Ships, Laden with Paſſengers, and Servants: two years before they mov'd with their main Body, and Pattent Government, which were fully Furniſhed with a Paſtor and Teacher, Worthy <hi>Higgiſon</hi> and <hi>Skelton,</hi> and all Materials, for Complea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of a Church of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Divine Inſtitution: Who ſafely Arriving according to their predeterminate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Inlargement of Chriſt's Kingdom, and His Majeſty of <hi>England</hi>'s Dominion: Firſtly, they ſet up their Standards, Dethroning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, they caſt him out of Heaven; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond time memorial, he had in the Natives Conſciences, and by Turf and Twig they took poſſeſſion of this his large Continent, and ſet up the firſt Church in theſe Parts, in a place they then called <hi>Salem;</hi> at which Convention, the Teſtimony which the Lord of all the Earth bore unto it, is wonderfully memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by a Saving Work upon a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of Quality,<note place="margin">Major General <hi>Gibbins.</hi>
               </note> who afterwards was the Chieftain and Flower of <hi>New-England</hi>'s Militia, and an Eminent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument both in Church and Commonwealth; he being the younger Brother of the Houſe of an Honourable Extract, his Ambition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding what he could expect at home, Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100210:8"/>bither: Before one Stone was laid in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Structure, or our Van-Currier's Arrival, he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no Debauchee, but of a Jocund Temper, and one of the Merry Mounts Society, who choſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather to Dance about a <hi>May pole,</hi> firſt Erected to the Honour of <hi>Strumpet Flora,</hi> than to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a good Sermon; who hearing of this Meeting, though above Twenty Miles diſtant from it, and deſirous to ſee the Mode and Novel of a Churches Gathering; with great ſtudiouſneſs he applyed himſelf to be at it; where behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their orderly procedure, and their method of ſtanding forth, to declare the Work of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon their Souls, being pricked at the Heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſprung forth among them, deſirous to be one of the Society, who though otherwiſe wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> acompliſhed, yet divinely illiterate, was ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> convinc'd and judged before all the ſecret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his heart being made manifeſt, fell down and Worſhipped God, to their aſtoniſhment, ſaying, <hi>That God was in them of a Truth;</hi> the Verity hereof, as long ſince it hath been affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by old Planters, ſo by his own Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, found after his Death it's confirmed; he about that time Lamenting his Chriſtleſs Eſtate, which evidenceth that it ought to be ſaid of that Sion, <hi>This man was Born there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One winterafter theſe good ſpies had view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Land, who ſent letters of the proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous good hand of Providence upon them, the taſte of the fruits of this Countrie, was ſweeter, and more welcome to their Principalls in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100210:9"/>then the Grapes of <hi>Eſchol</hi> were to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ld.</p>
            <p>The Leaders of this People upon ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate, drew up a Determination to ſettle the Corporation, and government, upon the Place: and Deputy to abide there, which being effected, and Divinely directed in ſuch a Choice of the Governour, the Famous Pattern of Wiſdom, Juſtice and Liberality, and of a Deputy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who by his Experience at Home, and Travels Abroad, with his Natural and Acquired A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bilities, was a Gentleman qualified above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the chief Rule and Government<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein according to his juſt Deſerts, he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more than others; the Fame whereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come Abroad in the Nation to ſuch whoſe hearts God had touched; this being upon the wing, there wanted not Number of Perſons of all Occupations, skill'd in all Faculties, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Planting of a Collony, who filled up a Fleet of Eleven Ships, of conſiderable Burthen, beſides their Attenders; ſome of them about Four Hundred Tuns, the reſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much inferiour; ſome carrying near Two Hundred Paſſengers, the reſt proportionably; the Wheels of Providence were lifted up very high, and alſo were radiantly magnificent.</p>
            <p>Theſe Tarting Travellers Removal, carrying ſo great a Reſemblance of Departure into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World, they were not ſtupid Stoicks,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100210:9"/>but abounded with that which Grace doth no deſtroy, but direct: What ſhowers of melting Tears dropt into the Boſomes of each other whoſe <hi>Souls</hi> as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> clave one to another, yet alleviated with conſideration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though they were <hi>Abſent in Body, yet Preſent in Spirit,</hi> and of their mutual acceſs to the Throne of Grace, and of <hi>Meeting at the Aſſembly of the Firſt-born, and Spirits of Juſt Men made Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> Some of their choice Friends, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> and others, went along with them from <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> to <hi>South-hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> where they parted, and he Preacht his Farewel Sermon.</p>
            <p>That ſo many Eminent Perſons, ſome of Noble Extract, ſhould upon Sea-Bridges, paſs over the largeſt Ocean in the Univerſe, by the good hand of their God upon them, having ſought of him a right way for themſelves, Little Ones, and Subſtance; yea above Three Thouſand in one Year, and that above Three Hundred Ships ſince that time; all Laden with Jewels of Invaluable Value, far above the Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> that each individual one ſhould have a Caeleſtial Convoy, under the Flaming Swords of Flying Cherubims, turning every way, to keep them in their way, ſo as they all at their Port ſafely Arrived: Not one Foundered in the Sea, Split upon Rocks, were ſuckt in by Sands, Over-ſet by ſudden Guſts, nor Taken and Plundered by Pirates on Robbers, except one called the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> whoſe Tutular
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100210:10"/>Guardiau Ship failed (if any Aboard put truſt therein) ſhe was Laden with Paſſengers for <hi>Boſton,</hi> but put in at <hi>Pemiquid,</hi> where the Ship and whole Cargo periſhed, but not one Soul of Seamen, or Paſſengers miſcarried; they met with an Hurricane, before or ſince not known in this Country, Raiſed by the Power of him, who holds the Wind in his Hand, and Commiſſioneth the Prince of the Air, by Raiſing <hi>Stormy Winds to fulfil his Word;</hi> it's ſaid, the Tide roſe Twenty Foot perpen dicular, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove its ordinary height. The ſame time, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother great Ship, Laden with Paſſengers was wonderfully preſerved, when as ready to be Split in pieces upon Rocks at the <hi>Iſle of Shoals;</hi> at the Prayer of the diſtreſſed Saints Aboard, God cauſed the Winds to Vere a Point or two about the Compaſs, ſo as ſhe cleared them, &amp; they were ſaved; <hi>in the Mount the Lord was ſeen;</hi> in this Ship was the Reverend Mr. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> three or four of his Sons, and whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, with a multitude of other precious Souls, among whom was the Worthy <hi>Jonathan Mitchel,</hi> then being a Lad.</p>
            <p>The like Salvation about the ſame time was vouchſafed to a great Ship Laden with Paſſengers, Bound for <hi>New-England,</hi> the Famous <hi>Norton,</hi> and Great <hi>Shepheard,</hi> with their Wives, were Aboard of her: They were forced back from the Channel, into <hi>North-Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> Road, where, though the Wind was off the Shoar, the Storm was ſo violent, as all their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100210:10"/>Anchors and Cables would not bring her up, and being in great danger of Foundering in the Sands, they were forced to cut both Main Maſt, and Fore Maſt by the Board, with Sail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Rigging; this <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> while able to ſtand, went from Cabbin to Cabbin to Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Pray with the Diſtreſſed Paſſengers, and Seamen, who by one Wave were waſhed Over-board, and the next Wave threw them Aboard again; there was great Crying out then, <hi>What ſhall we do to be Saved?</hi> At the Prayers of theſe Men of God, this Ship and every Soul Aboard was given them; the nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Day they all Landed ſafe, and as ſoon as A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhoar, two Vipers deſigned not only to Leap upon the hands of them both, but to ſeiz their Perſons; but how ſtangely preſerved is not un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>known to ſome of us; though the Houſe was beſet by them, when as they were at a pious Meeting, (then called a Conventicle.) Next Year they Arrived all ſafe at <hi>Boſton;</hi> the Ship for that Year was Diſinable,</p>
            <p>Ought we not now to cry out, conſidering the Circumſtances, Oh! <hi>The Wheel, the Wheel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> He who ſits upon the Throne, appeared with the Rainbow about his Head, and the Spirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Living Creatures was in the Wheels, from their Original Motion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Waves obeyed the Voice, and the Wind ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled the Pleaſure of the Lord of the Univerſe,</hi> ſo a the firſt whole Fleet Arrived ſafe in a ſmal time, without Loſs of any but of one perſon</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100210:11"/>
            <p>Theſe Nobly Grateful Paſſengers, appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſet apart a Day of Thanksgiving to the Almighty God, for the great Goodneſs and nighty Works they had ſeen in their Vovage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd with <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, having found reſt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſoles of their Feet, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ched forth from their Floating Arks, and Celebrated the High P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of him, who had thus graciouſly and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfully Safe guarded them, and Landed them; <hi>They Sang the Song of Moſes, and of the Lamb,</hi> whom they in this Voyage had followed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow paid their Vows to God to Serve him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Build him an Habitation, and according to he Examples of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their ſafe Landing, and Arrival, each Built <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Altar to <hi>Jehova,</hi> ſo they (being content <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith Huts and ſmoaky Cottages) firſt applyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelves to Build the Lord an Habitation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore they ſet up their own Houſes, and Join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in Church-Fellowſhip, ſetting up the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Sions</hi> Throne, in his Order and Worſhip; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving ſix Eminent Miniſters, who came along <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith them, and divers Hundreds of Choice Materials. Thus far an Abbreviate of this Colonies Foundation, and manner of its Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng.</p>
            <p>The good News from this far Country, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om theſe men of Deſires, being ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ied into <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngland,</hi> was as Cold Waters to a thirſty Soul; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Stile of their Letters was ſo full of Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ravity, and of a Gracious Savour, ſo grateful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe of full Age, who by reaſon of Uſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100210:11"/>had their Senſes exerciſed, to diſcern both good and evil, as it put them upon ſtudy, to increaſe their Number, ſtirring up each other to get among them to <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grace powred into the Hearts and Lips of theſe firſt Planters, dropt down into Pens of private Chriſtians, like ſweet ſmelling Myrrh, ſo as they began their Letters with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical benediction, and concluded them with Salutations; a Letter then from <hi>New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and for a conſiderable time after, was Venerated as a Sacred Script, or as the Writing or ſome Holy Prophet, 'twas carried many Miles, where divers came to hear it, becauſe the <hi>Savour of Chriſt's Name was as good Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment powred forth, therefore the Virgins Lov'd Him;</hi> and a multitude of pious Souls through the whole Nation, were in their Spirits preſſed to Joyn in this Work, ſo as their Malignant Obſervers in their Words and Writings,<note place="margin">Burtons Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly</note> Rendred them: <hi>Furijs Religionis Acti.</hi> Men acted by <hi>Religious Furies,</hi> and the Feſtuſſ's of thoſe Times, declared them to be perſons Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, ſaying of their much Religion, as he ſaid of <hi>Pauls</hi> much Learning, that it had made them mad.</p>
            <p>In a ſhort time after their Arrival, a Snake crept forth, which Lay Latent in the Tender Graſs, one who pretended himſelf a Religious Reformado, and to withdraw from the Noiſe of Secular Affairs, came over in the firſt Fleet,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100210:12"/>he offered to Joyn in Church-Fellowſhip here, but was refuſed upon ſuſpicion to be what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he proved to be, <hi>viz.</hi> a Roman Catholick, and of ſuch Note among them,<note place="margin">Chriſtopher Gardner</note> as he had at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Received the Orders of the Knighthood, (there called the Holy Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre) which Order he appeared to be of, by Letters intercepted, ſent by a man of Place in <hi>England,</hi> a profeſt Enemy to this Colony; thus Satan's Proto-Emiſſary againſt this People, was diſcovered in his prime Plot, and ſecret Snare, who deſigned to ſmother this Embrio Colony, or to Strangle this Babe, not yet out of its Swadling Bands; for which Deliverance, high Praiſes were Celebrared to the Name of <hi>Sions</hi> Saviour.</p>
            <p>Not long after, a deſperate Myne was ſprung by this Peoples Grand Adverſary, according to Advice of a Politician elſewhere, to Blow up Religion, by Religion, Encouraging the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty this People had obtained to Leave their Nation, ſaying, Let them go, by their Parties and Factions, as their Brethren at <hi>Leyden</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had done, ſo they would deſtroy each other; but the Lord moſt graciouſly Countermined it, for the Deſign of both the Magiſtrates and Miniſters, with the Body of this People, was not with the Rigid Separatiſts to Caſt off all Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but to act the part of the good old Nonconformiſts, who though they could
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100210:12"/>not Cloſe with the Hierarchy, nor with the Corruptions in Diſcipline and Worſhip, yet in her Faith and Doctrine, they own'd her to be their Mother; and therefore having by Pattent-Charter from His Majeſty, a Grant to Remove, they peaceably Improved the ſame, and left their Native Land; and at their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, they drew up, and Publiſhed a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſto to the whole Nation, of the Grounds of this their Undertaking; not knowing, whether ever they ſhould ſee Land, ſtyling thoſe whom they parted from, in their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="request">
                        <head>REVEREND FATHAERS AND BRETHREN.</head>
                        <p>The Humble Request of His Majesties Loyal Subjects, The <hi>GOVERNOUR</hi> and <hi>COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PANY</hi> of <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To the reſt of their Brethren, in and of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> For the obtaining of their Prayers, and Removal of their Suſpicions, and Miſrepreſentations of their Intentions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> John Bellamy, <date>
                                 <hi>1630.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Their Subſcription Signed was <hi>Your Aſſured Friends and Brethren,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Iohn Winthrop <hi>Governour.</hi>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Saltonſtall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Iſaac Iohnſon.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Tho. Dudley <hi>Deputy Governour.</hi>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100210:13"/>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Charles Fines.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>George Phillips.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed> Cum multis ajiis.</closer>
                        <trailer>From <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> Ab ard the <hi>Arabella,</hi> April 7th. <hi>1630.</hi>
                        </trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>THeſe Magnanimous Heroes, whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is Pleſſed, whoſe Names not only during <hi>New England,</hi> hath a Being, but ſhall be had in <hi>Everlasting Remembrance,</hi> they then declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though there might be ſome among them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, yet they were not of them, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Remembrance in their Prayers, (as above) in this their dangerous Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not long after this, Mr.</hi> Cottons <hi>Farewel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (above mentioned) was Printed as</hi> London, <hi>and ſince Re printed at</hi> Boſton, <hi>Entituled,</hi> GODS PROMISE TO HIS PLANTATION, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he <hi>Exhorted them to Remember</hi> England, <hi>their Mother, and that they ſhould not be like thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Birds, who when they had</hi> Swum over a Stream <hi>or River, forgot the Wing that had Hatcht them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Serpent ſoon got into this Eden, and according to his Maxime acted, divide, and Overcome, he ſow'd the Seed of Diſcord, &amp; Diviſion among us, ſo as this Heterodoxy was Preached publickly, that there was no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100210:13"/>Communion to be held with the Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England;</hi> and that if any of our Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers had tranſiently heard a Miniſter, which Conformed to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> declaring Repentance for it, he was to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>communicated, and that no Communion wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be held, with any Unregenerate Perſon that they ought not to Pray, or Crave a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing at Meals, before Wife, or any Relation Unconverted, of which Converſion their Opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion was the Teſt; and not only ſo, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Oath of Allegiance to His Majeſty was not to be taken, nor was it lawful to take any other kind of Oath, becauſe no Power to be Setled by Oath, but Chriſts Kingly Power only, and that our Pattent ought to be ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> back to our King; nor ought we to have to do therewith: Thus was <hi>Now-England</hi> Attack by Satan; and this from an Eminent Preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, noted for Piety in his Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, as his ſtricteſt Obſervers Characteriſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him. This Child of Light walked in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs about Forty Years, not only by Rejecting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and its Baptiſm, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſecond Baptiſm alſo.</p>
            <p>Taking up the Seekers perſwaſion looking for new Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Roger Williams.</note> yet di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not his Root turn into Rottenneſs the Root of the Matter abode i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, as by his Faithful Defence of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>damentals of Chriſtian Religion, in a public<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſpute; and about the Year 1677. puttin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100210:14"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut a Book againſt the Quakers: Thus the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord infinite in Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſed of Satans Malice, ſo as he was Out ſhot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his own Bow, the Lord held the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and Miniſtry in Unity, according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntegrity of their hearts, ſo as this ſmall new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igged Veſſel was preſerved againſt this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent Storm, which the Prince of Darkneſs Raiſed upon her at firſt ſetting forth, with Deſign to have Overſet and Foundred her; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus was Munificent Mercy magnified toward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is People, when ſew in Number, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir low Eſtate; ſuch was the Conduct of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that they kiſſed each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er in the Mount of God.</p>
            <p>The Report of this admirable Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence with this People in their Civiland Sacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dminiſtrations, Reach'd our Nation even to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he aſtoniſhment of thoſe who caſt no good Eye upon us, but to the Encouragement of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe otherwiſe minded, ſo as that the Well-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffected came over as Clouds, and like Doves to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Windows; ſuch was their Increaſe, that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>even years time, the <hi>Maſſachuſet</hi> Patient could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot contain them. This Vine ſpread forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Branches on the other ſide of this Bay, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a <hi>Rehoboth;</hi> it's ſaid that about this time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Two Years there came over Seventy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hips, who one with another Tranſported an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undred Paſſengers, to the aſtoniſhment of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſober part of our Nation. At which time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d before, as the Harveſt was great &amp; white,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100210:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo the Lord thereof thruſt forth not only L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bourers, but multiplied <hi>Aholiabs,</hi> and <hi>Bezaliell</hi> Robbing our Nation, to ſupply this peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with ſuch as were filled with the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Wiſdom and Underſtanding, in all Spiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Skill, in the Structure and Furniture of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great Work, and about ſetting up the Tabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacle of the Congregation, and the Ark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Teſtimony, according to the Pattern i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Mount. Of whom a Quaternion, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> Eminent for Spiritual Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and <hi>Mather</hi> for Caeleſtial Dying, <hi>Hook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for Soul Fiſhing, <hi>Stone</hi> for Building up i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Holy Faith: three of whom came in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame Ship, and one of them not long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the Reverend <hi>John Davenport,</hi> the famo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> of <hi>Rowley,</hi> beſides the Worthy Fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fruits of <hi>New-England;</hi> the Proto-Paſtors an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Teachers, whom our Pen fails to Enumerate ſuch was the Cloud of them who came ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt and laſt; ſeventy ſeven Miniſters and fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Young Students fit for the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Theſe voluntary Exiles for the Word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and Teſtimony of Jeſus, having be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> under Exerciſe of Spirit, and Burthened b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mens ſetting up their Poſts and Threſholds, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Gods Poſts and Threſholds; and now War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lively Senſe of Gods preſervin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goodneſs, and ſafe Landing of them, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedious paſſage ſome Encountred; tho' ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had but ſix Weeks, others Twenty and od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Weeks durance, yet without Loſs or Famiſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100210:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of one perſon; all this while ſhut up, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afeguarded about four inches diſtance from Death: Theſe Votaries being under the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their late Obligations, they Anointed <hi>Jacobs</hi> Pillar, then they had opportunity, and accordingly Bewail'd, and were aſhamed of their Miſdoings, begg'd pardon and aſſiſtance from the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh, and direction from on High, to ſet up the Throne, and Place of the Soles of Chriſts Feet; after ſolemn Imploring the Diſcovery of the Form, and Faſhion of Gods Houſe, the Comings in, and Goings out of the Church of God, which is the Houſe of God, the Ground and Pillar of Truth; they agreed upon the practice of that which is called the Way of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Churches, which for Thirteen Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they Walkt in the practice of, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Synod further confirmed the ſame, as is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fterwards notified; which Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, was Publiſhed to the Europaean World, in the Book of the Keyes, <hi>and Vindication of the Way of the Congregational Churches in</hi> New: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, pen'd by the Reverend Teacher of <hi>Boston</hi> Church, and other worthy Scripts, by divers Worthy Miniſters of this Country, in Anſwer to the Reproach put upon them, by ſome Eminent Divines, elſewhere of a Mr. <hi>Samuel</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother perſwaſion; yet one <hi>Rutherford.</hi> of their Chieftains for Piety In his <hi>Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and Learning, Declared in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ual Antichriſt.</hi> Print, his full Aſſent to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100210:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Book of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> in all its particularities, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in one punc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilio about of the power of Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nods, which as he apprehended, the book o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Keyes</hi> did too much ſtreighten.</p>
            <p>The Lords preſence with our Fathers in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Civil and Sacred Concerns, ſignally appeared with our Honourable Counſellers; our Pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Ancient, the Mighty Man, and the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of War, the Judge and the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ophet, our Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and our Rulers; though none of them General Governour, yet as by ſome it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat been well obſerved, ſome of them were gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally Governours, eſpecially the firſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our, who in Twenty Years was above ten time Governour, &amp; the firſt Deputy Governour, but li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſs: ſuch was the deep Humility of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Elevated Men, that upon Election Days, the provoked the Free-men, to make uſe of the Liberty againſt their own intentions.</p>
            <p>Never ſo ſmall a ſpot of Land, was ſo hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly favoured with ſuch an Aggregate of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of ſuch Abilities in Divine and Humane Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as <hi>New-England</hi> then was; ſo as up the Emergency of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Witſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> firſt Paſtor of <hi>Boston</hi> Church, Return into <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> he with conſent of his Church, left t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> care of his Flock to Mr. <hi>Winthrop,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dudly,</hi> they being then the much Honour Governour, and Deputy Covernour of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> People, who both accepted, and perform'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Charge: Knowing well; that the Princes <hi>Juda</hi> in King <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> Reign, were appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Teach the People in the Law of God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100210:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t's certainly Recorded, That above an Hundred Years before that time, there were five Paſtors in the Reformed Church at <hi>Orleans</hi> in <hi>France</hi> at one time, the major part of whom were Lords, and Barons of the Nation; ſo high an Eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate was then put upon this Sacred Function.</p>
            <p>Beſides their Dexteriry in Handling of the Civil, and the Lords Two-Edged Sword; it's not to be forgotten, (though above ſeven times ſeven years ſince) the skill they were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd with, &amp; was ſhown in their being Verſed in the uſe of the Military Sword, at <hi>Fox-Hills</hi> Fort Action, where they as two Tactiques, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et their Armies in Battle Array, each appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng General in the Head of a Body, at <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton,</hi> where all the Cavalry and Infantry of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Country appeared; ſhewing ſuch real <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcipline in their Field Exerciſe, by rowling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>renches making their Approaches, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yling the Fort, &amp; by orderly Sallies, defending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſame together with a Naval Combate on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth ſides, ſuch as in none of the Gallantry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Bravery of all our General Traynings ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d appear; thus the Motions of the Wheels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere very high and terrible to our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and ſo were the Rings and Wheels of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rovidence full of Eyes, to ſupply all our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ants, ſo as when this People, though never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uced to Famine, yet oft to ſhort Commons; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as when Bread failed, Fiſh and Herbs was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry good Fare.</p>
            <p>Then not only <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships were ſent in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100210:16"/>with Sheep, Kine, and Mares, to compleat our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arms and Husbandry; but rather then Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tle Flock, who had followed him into this Wilderneſs, (upon the hearing of his voice.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould want, their good Shepherd Spirited the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eat <hi>Strafford,</hi> and Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Commiſſioned him to be their Purveyor, out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his <hi>Iriſh Stalls</hi> and Stores to ſupply their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; yea, ſuch was Chriſts paſtoral reſpects <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them, leaſt they ſhould be neglected: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> muſt Buy a Ship of Burthen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade her, and Tranſport it to them at his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt.</p>
            <p>There wanted not Obſerved of this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les Methods and Meaſures, who failed not to miſrepreſent the General Muſter before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oned, and all other their Actions, who ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red us, that as we had caſt off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Yoke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſcopacy, ſo we deſigned to caſt off our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>giance and Loyalty to His Majeſties Crown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Dignity, which never entred into the Hearts of our Grave Sages; they knew better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen ſo, that under God it was their only ſhield <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd buckler, againſt all violent Intruders, and ſpecially the <hi>French,</hi> who at our Arrival here, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere not Seiz'd of <hi>Accady,</hi> then called <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cotia;</hi> our Brethren <hi>of Scotland,</hi> were then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſeſſed of <hi>Port Royal,</hi> and above two years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter, they having Built a Fort there, but the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rench</hi> purchaſing it <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> poſſeſſed it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd would then own no <hi>N. Engl.</hi> and juſtified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Kings Claims to all the Continent on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100210:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>this ſide <hi>Virginia.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Governour at <hi>Port Royal</hi> Addreſt his Letters to our Covernour to Monſieur Monſieur <hi>J. W. Governour of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>at</hi> Boſton <hi>in</hi> Accady; and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Subſcription Ryled himſelf D. C. <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of</hi> Accady; thereby declaring unto us, That we improved his Maſters Dominions. The <hi>Dutch</hi> on the other ſide claimed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necticut,</hi> and had there ſet up a Fort, and Trading Houſe in that River, ſo as we were ſurrounded with bad Neighbours.</p>
            <p>This Miſpriſion ſo far prevailed, as a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Machine was Formed againſt this Country, not to put a demurr or ceſſation to their proceedure, but to ſubvert and overthrow this Colonies Foundation, ſo miraculouſly Founded and Multiplied; ſo as the Pattent was call'd in, and ſent for to be delivered up; a New Commiſſion and Regulation drawn up confirmed, and ſent over; whereby this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter all Difficulties, and Dangers of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting themſelves, and Settlement here, were reduced to harder meaſure, then if they had not left their Nation, altho' upon as great ſecurity as could humanely be given.</p>
            <p>Then all our worthy Patriots, in each polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Zorobbabel,</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhua,</hi> and all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Land, being deeply affected, afflicted, and ſorely diſtreſſed, they firſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt the Divine Throne, where this halting <hi>Jacob,</hi> upon his Wraſting with the Angel o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> found Grace with him, that his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100210:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Name was then changed into <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and had power from him ſo that prevailing with God he alſo prevailed with man.</p>
            <p>They Supplicated our Gracious King, and the Lords Commiſſioners of the Forreign Plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations, proſtrating themſelves at His Majeſtie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Foot-ſtool: <hi>Beſought that they might be made th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Objects of his Royal Clemency, that this poor Plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation which had found ſo much favour from God, more then others, might not find the leſs from man.</hi> The Kings heart being in the Hand of the Lord, was turned about as Rivers of Waters ſo as this Weapon Formed againſt this people proſpered not, and by Divine Hand was bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken; as well as a great Ship new Built purpoſely to have brought over, the Artificers and Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nagers of this Engine, whoſe Back was afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſtrange manner broken on the Stocks; ſo a this Tool for about Forty Years wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laid aſide and then for our Iniquities, was new Forged Furbiſhed, and took effect; in which time, in credible was the Increaſe of His Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects in this his Dominion, being Sown with the Seed of Man and Beaſt, to the Honour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our God, King, and Nation, far exceeding the Number which the Exchequer of any Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in <hi>Europe</hi> could have Effected: God then ſaid, this ſhall not be; for which an Alta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was Erected, <hi>Jehova Niſſi,</hi> The Hand upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>Satan being Diſpoſeſſed of ſo great a part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Dominion, attempts its recovery, by ſtirring
<pb facs="tcp:100210:18"/>up the Pequods, who were the Terror of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Salvages, in theſe Parts, who to the Glory of <hi>Iſraels</hi> God, and the Natives Amazement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in a little above one years time were Deſtroy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed; this <hi>Amaleck</hi> fell upon our Rere in our Feeble Eſtate, <hi>Moſes</hi> Hands being held up by <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur, Joſhua</hi> obtained a great Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Our Fathers Cryed unto God, who heard them, and they were Saved; this Pequod <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malecks</hi> Name (according to Gods Oath,) hath been ever ſince blotted out from under our Heaven. Thus was the Lord his Peoples Banners.</p>
            <p>The Dragons old indefatigable Malice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, in a moſt ſubtile Stratagem contrived, by letting out of his Mouth a Flood to Drown the Woman and Male Child, fled into this Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to be fed; which made this little World groan to ſee it ſelf ſurrounded with Famileſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal &amp; Antinomian Hereſies &amp; Errors; this chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly befel <hi>Boſton</hi> and its Vicinity, which Church Glorying in their Candleſtick, being furniſhed with two ſuch Burning and Shining Lights, a Paſtor and Teacher, who for Love and Light Out-ſhined all others; and in the Gifts of Knowledge and Utterance of divers of their Brethren; the Serpents ſubtilty ſhew'd it ſelf in a Multitudinariſm of Queſtions, ſtarted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of ſeeking Light; Error cloath'd it ſelf under diſguiſe of Truth by pretext of Magnifying Grace, it was turned into Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all this under the Umbrage of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100210:18"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eacher, who tho' he had Sown only good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed in Gods Field, yet the Enemy came and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wed Tares; as he upon a Faſt-Day in <hi>Boston</hi> Church, before the Country, vindicated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf; that whilſt men ſlept, this miſchief was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, which was the Subject of that days Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſe, and he diſcriminated between them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>penly declaring, what good Seed he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own, and its diſſimilitude from the Tares which the Enemy had Sown, proving by <hi>Jerom</hi> &amp; Authentick Authors, That the Tares in <hi>Judea,</hi> were ſo like the Wheat, that until the Harveſt, without great difficulty they could be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; thus Hells Cataracts were ſet open, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a multitude of Errors then were broached, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the hazard of the ruine of the Churches, with many Hereſies deſtroying the Foundation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut as of old, when Arrianiſm prevailed, the Earth helpt the Woman; ſo many took oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity to greaten their outward Eſtates, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever befel them upon any other account; oh! That men would praiſe the Lord for his Good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, and for the Work of this Sions Saviour in delivering from this Maſter-plot of Hell, who deſigned the ruine of theſe Churches and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but by Divine Benediction upon the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures taken by Magiſtrates in the Court, and the Elders and Churches in the Synod, that was prevented which threatned the Deſtruction of all, but chiefly of <hi>Boſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Churches and People of <hi>New-England</hi> had for a conſiderable time, Enjoyed Peace and
<pb facs="tcp:100210:19"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, Trade at Home, and Traffick Abroad, they greatned their Eſtate by Building ſmall Veſſelt, and ſome conſiderable Ships, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of Timber for the <hi>Indies</hi> and <hi>Iſlands,</hi> tho' not without Alarms from the Indians, and other Afflictive Providences, the Lord took us into his Fatherly Hand, by Droughts, Blaſts upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grain; yea, by Feavers, and Small pox, and with one great Fire; but in the interim, being without any Adverſary or ſuch evil Occurrent, they lookt at it as a Duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon them, to draw up a Plat Form of Diſcipline, and Church Covernment, which might be laid as a Foundation, for the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come: And the rather, becauſe the Way they practiſed, was queſtioned by ſome, whether it was agreeable to the Rule of Gods Word, whereupon a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ill was drawn up by the General Court, for Aſſembling of a Synod; after debate, it was agreed unto, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Synod of Elders and Brethren, according to the firſt Preſident of a Synod or Council Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Sacred Leaves of the Acts and Monuments of the Apoſtles who Aſſembled at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> theſe did Convene, to whom we may aſſign, as hath been Obſerved by one of Note in the Churches of Chriſt: <hi>That as theſe had ſhewn more Love and Zeal to Communion with God in his Pure Worſhip, in their Hazardous Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings into theſe Parts, So God did more for them, in ſhewing them the Scriptural Way of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as a Divine Favour, and Boon vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
<pb facs="tcp:100210:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>unto them, then he did to any other, which Lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath not been hid in a Buſhel, but reſplended not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> into our Nution, but into all the Reformed Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Concerning theſe men, it may without arr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gancy be affirmed, tho' they were of low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtature then our firſt Refo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mers, who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> immortal Name, yet having the advantage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtanding upon their Gigantine Shoulders, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had opportuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of ſeeing further, then tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Giants did; ſome of them made diſcovery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Papal Antichriſt, and of his Tyranny ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Kings, Princes, and Prelates; others thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> down the Epiſcopal Uſurpation over their Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low Presbyters, and reduced them to their Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitive Parity, and the Church Diſcipline the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Eſtabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed, eſpecially the Later at <hi>Geneva</hi> conſidering the vaſt Number in their Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bodies, conſiſting from Eight to Twelve Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand Members in one Congregation, ſo as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had from two to five Paſtors in one Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in divers, ſix Ruling Elders; the publick Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nagement of Diſcipline, upon Offenders in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vaſt an Auditory &amp; Aſſembly would have tende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Scandal of the Reformation, &amp; have hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred the progreſs of Proteſtantiſm; they pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dently concluded, to commit it into the priva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands of the Claſſies, <hi>viz.</hi> Paſtors and Ruli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Elders of each Church, if need required f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther conſideration, to be Tryed by the Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quoy of the Neighbour Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> the Paſtors and Elders there to be Repreſented, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for a reſult of it to be determined by the Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100210:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Province, which if not there accompliſht, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be finally concluded by the National Synod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the Churches; could there have been a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore prudential way of Church Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ched upon, then that which they practiſed; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d doubtleſs God accepted the ſincere deſires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Servants hearts, to the Converſion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dification of many thouſands in their moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Faith; but our Reformers circumſtances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere vaſtly different, our number fewer, &amp; thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ninently qualified for further Reformation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey being a ſelect choice Company (&amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it offence it may be ſaid) of the Cream and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower of our Nation, not only for Morality, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Piety; having been, both Miniſters &amp; People, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der Sufferings for the Truc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; Worſhip of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, both Confeſſors and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofeſſors, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rvour of Spirit brought into this ſolitary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, where they had opportunity of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of God, freed from Temptations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich populous places might have expoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em unto, and from the Baits of Honours &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rofits which other places might have preſented <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> They after near two years ſeeking of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſerious ſearching out his Will, with Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mity of heart, and mind agreed, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich then was, and now is called the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orm of Church Diſcipline; as for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion of Faith, they wholly agreed with that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t forth by the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſtee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After full Anſwer was given to every Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100210:20"/>which every individual perſon cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> make, both in Churches and Towns; both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them having had the conſideration of it put u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to them, the Plat Form above mentioned wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accepted of, and declared by the Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Court, and all the Churches, as being fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſubſtance of it, what they had hithert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practiſed in all the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ebes, as before is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſerved, and being that which was agreeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Word of God, and the principles of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Congregational Way, firſt practiſed in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Churches, &amp; for a good time ſince; this Plat fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hath been Printed here, and in <hi>England,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> publiſhed Abroad to the World, there being n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> difference between us, and the other Reformed Churches, whether the Church of <hi>England,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Churches, but only in point o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church Government, as to points of Faith an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doctrine, we all agree in one; this we though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> needful to inlarge upon, humbly fearing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords preſent Controverſy with us, doth it great meaſure Center here, <hi>viz.</hi> our deviating<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and receeding from that which gave us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name of <hi>New England; viz.</hi> the Plat-Form and agreed practice of our Churches, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>The Ravening Wolves of Hereſy, and the wild Boars of Tyranny, being chained up from Devouring the Lords poor I lock, and from Rooting up his Heritage.</p>
            <p>The unreconcileable Adverſary, lets looſe his Foxes with Fire brands at their Tails, te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urn
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100210:21"/>up this peoples ſtanding Corn, which no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking, he ſent forth his Foxes, the <hi>little Foxes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſpoil this Vine, in the time of its tender Grapes but the Keeper of this Vineyard neither ſlumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor ſleeping,</hi> took and deſtroy'd them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Watch'd, Warded, and every momen Watered it, and none did hurt it, much leſs threw down the Stone-Wall thereof; tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many an hard puſh and ſhuff was made at it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was then a <hi>Burthenſome Stone,</hi> &amp; their Governours like a Torch of Fire in a Sheaf, many an <hi>Ebenezar,</hi> Stones of help di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Fathers then ſet up, for which the Lords Sacro ſanct Name was Celebrated.</p>
            <p>This preceeding Relation is but as a few Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Ephraims</hi> Grapes, compared with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy of <hi>Abiezer, our Fathers</hi> Helpers Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; ſo many unimaginable and unutterable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acts of Favour, and preventing Mercies, were in the Revolution of twenty five, or about thirty years ſpace vouchſafed to our Fathers, as would fill a large Volume, yet not without mixture of Fatherly Corrections, to evince Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Reſpects unto them, as their own words writ into our Nation teſtify; that they were by the Dew from above, and Caeleſtial Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces kept alive, and cheriſhed; as to the ſequel, we ſhall leave it to ſuch Sprightly and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Wits to perform, who ſhall eſpouſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knowing that tract of time will admit liberty of freer Diſcourſe about Matters, then this Age will bear; the Relator being in hazard <hi>of</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100210:21"/>having his Teeth daſht out, by Truth liftin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up her heeles, if he come too near her, as hat been Experienced and Recorded by our Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons Great Hiſtoriographer.</p>
            <p>This was the time <hi>of our Fathers Love of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eſpouſals, and Kindneſs of their Youth, they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen Holineſs unto the Lord, and the Firſt Fruits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Increaſe.</hi> God Rode upon the Heavens fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their help, they dewlt ſafely, tho' ſolitarily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Iſſachar</hi> Rejoyced in their Tents, and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lebulon</hi> in his Going forth, but have we brought Sacrifices unto the Holy Mountain; though we have ſucked of the abundance and treaſures of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Sea, to the enriching of divers. This Tribe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath aboundantly multiplied to the admiration of all Beholders.</p>
            <p>So as a noted <hi>Belgian</hi> one of the Eaſt India Company, who above twenty years ſince have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng heard of the fame of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place, purpoſely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame over to take a view of it, and paſt through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the parts of it, and made a particular remark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon our ſea trade, and the incredible number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ſmall Veſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls he then ſaw, beſides ſome Ships <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f conſiderable Burthen belonging to us.</p>
            <p>Nor is to be forgotten the anſwer made to a Meſſenger of the Nations, an Attendant upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>French</hi> Court, ſent hither by <hi>Lewis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rand,</hi> to demand the fulfilling of the Articles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade at <hi>Breda,</hi> between the two Crowns, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere to his aſtoniſhment ſaw, what he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot have believed; to him it was told, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od had founded this Sion, and that the poor
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100210:22"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his People did truſt in him; at his departure with wonderment he ſaid, <hi>Lo, what hath God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one!</hi> and if his Maſters ſervants did know how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e poor of this Country lived, he would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave one left.</p>
            <p>It might be then ſaid, who ſo happy as new <hi>New England,</hi> by the Lord their ſhield and Sword of their Excellency: as our Report hath paſſed through <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> ſo that <hi>Spain</hi> is no ſtranger to it,<note place="margin">C. Allin</note> appeareth by the Diſcourſe, which the Governour <hi>of Cuba</hi> had with a Priſoner of Note of ours falling into his hands, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our being a People eminent for great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ality and Reformation, but <hi>mind you</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow your Children will prove, and what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome of them;</hi> a Speech becoming a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man well Verſed in Sacred and Civil Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Thus far of the Light and white ſide of the Pillar, which attended us in this our Wilderneſs Pilgrimage; the black and dark ſide remains: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd we hope thus far we have cleared our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from being the procurers and peccant cauſes of theſe diſmal days now befallen us; they according to Divine Inſtitution walked with God, they did Juſtice and Judgment, and then it was well with them.</p>
            <p>The Lord took delight in our Fathers, and they in him; we have left the Lord, he hath forſaken us; they Walkt with him, we contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto him; he Subdued their <hi>Pequod</hi> and <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Enemies before them, gave their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100210:22"/>Country into our hands; but now the Sce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Affai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is turned, we are made a Spoil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Haters, to our Popiſh and Pagan Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bours, a Deriſion, we are ſold and ſcattered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mong the Heathen; can we ſay, <hi>All this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> befallen us, yet have we not forgotten thee, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have we done falſely in thy Covenant;</hi> this w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> fear is our mortal wound, <hi>viz.</hi> the forget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of our Fathers and of our God, we have dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> falſely in our own and their Covenant, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtipulated for us; this is the quarrel which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Holy God is now avenging: Hath <hi>Chittim</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Canada</hi> chang'd their Gods? <hi>Do we thus Requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord? Oh Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liſh People and Unwiſe!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O poor <hi>New-England,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Boſton,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Day of it, poor to a proverb, of being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loſt Town in our firſt Founding; thoſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Towns enquired, how the Mean On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lived here, the Rich had their Farms Abroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Subſiſt by, but as for the poor, how coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſubſiſt? The Anſwer was, their Miniſtry was ſo ſweet unto them, and the Bread of Lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo ſavoury to their Souls, that they forgot thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily Food, ſo welcome was Chriſtian Society to them, that he who had but an Acre of Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for his Houſe Lot, parted with one half of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to a deſirable Neighbour; he that had but hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Acre did the like: Thus were we increaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo as inſtead of a deſolate place, where ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fathers found no Town to dwell in, they Cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed unto the Lord hungry and thirſty, who le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them forth by a right way, that we are become
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100210:23"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſmall City of Habitation. God gave ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f them then a particular Faith upon Pſalm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>07.4. to 8. When as they were brought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mall ſtore of proviſion, upon the firſt Market Day by the General Court appointed to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ept, they put to Sail half of it, to handſel it with. Thus was this contemptible place raiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, ſo that in leſs then ſixty years, its Reputed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Mart of the <hi>North-America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That little Church which after ſeven years growth, its Number) in their Mud-wall Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Houſe with woodeu Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lices) was ſo ſmall, as a Child might have told the whole Aſſembly; it hath been ſo Amplified and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ified, by the Adorable Preſence of him, <hi>whoſe Countenance as the oun ſhining in his full ſtrength,</hi> with Radiant Beams through the Chryſtal Glaſs of the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iumvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te Miniſtry of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hree Succeſſive <hi>Johns, Walſon, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tton</hi> &amp; <hi>Norton,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each ſo full of the Spirit of Love, Light, and Learning, as ſcarcely parall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll'd in many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations; this Church is now grown up to be a Trinity Colledge of Churches, beſides three other Congregations, every Lords Day diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calling upon the Name of the Lord, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each of them of different perſwaſions: Oh that the Redeemed of the Lord, whom he hath Sav'd from the Hand of the Enemy, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from the Lands, might give thanks to the Lord, for <hi>his Goodneſs and Mercy Endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Anceſtors were men of God, made
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100210:23"/>partakers of the Divine Nature, Chriſt was form'd, and viſibly Legible in them, they Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed God in Houſes of the firſt Edition, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arge Chambers, or Windows, Cieled with Cedar, or painted with Vermilion; a company of plain, pious, humble and open heated Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, call'd Puritans; when News was brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ither, that the Church at <hi>Bermudas</hi> was Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh'd thence, into a deſolate Iſland, and full of St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aits, forthwith they ſent a Veſſel of good Burthen to them, fully Laden with proviſions of all ſorts, each ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing who ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt in ſo good a work; which ſupply came into them, when as all the Meal in their Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els, and Oil in their Cruiſe was ſpent; and it was brought to them upon a Lords-Day, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s their Faithful Paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had finiſhed his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, from Pſalm 23. <hi>To Truſt upon Jehova <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Shepherd, who would not ſuffer his Flock to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant;</hi> thus the Lord ſet his Seal to their Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Prayers.</p>
            <p>The Gravity of their Habit, and Calendar Reformation, by Satans Pollicy, hath fince been imitated by the Quakers, that our Fathers might be Lyſted among thoſe Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icks, and Enthuſiaſts; but they own'd no Spirit within them, but to be tryed by the Word without them, and no word without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, but accorded with the Spirit within them; no word of promiſe to them without a work of Grace upon them, neither without the Holy Spirits dwelling in them, and teſtifying
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100210:24"/>to them. They minded the Ornament of the meek and quiet Spirit, they were not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the toyes and fancies of this age, they were Glorious within, their clothing was of wrought gold, they were brought in unto the King, in rayment of needle work, wrought with tender pricks of conſcience; the leaſt vain fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, wanten, or wicked thought toucht them to the quick, ſenſibly feeling others adverſity, as being in the ſame body, inſtance in our <hi>Pequod</hi> and <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Wars, we were not the next concerned, it was <hi>Conecticut</hi> and <hi>Plimouth;</hi> at firſt no union of the <hi>Collonies,</hi> why ſhould we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our ſelves with them, why did they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo far a field, they might have contented themſelves,<note place="margin">Mr <hi>Oldham</hi>
               </note> wthout ſuch large accomodation. The firſt Engliſh Blood-ſhed, was of an <hi>Indian</hi> trader, and one who had been highly ſined for abuſing this authority, but it was Engliſh Blood, and they made Inquiſition after it.</p>
            <p>So they did, when a couple of Engliſh traders were at <hi>Richmond Iſland,</hi> ſlain by the Indians 1631. and the next year an Engliſh Pirate ſeized a veſſel, who robbed &amp; made ſpoil at <hi>Pemiquod</hi> Fort, and along the Coaſt; the worthy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Council then uſed means for their ſuppreſſion, and accordingly it ſucceded: Nation and Neighbourhood was Obligation to their engaging in the quarrel, they had ſimpathy in each joys and ſorrows, our ſenſeleſs ſtupidity, and our Pride devours our Charity, Oh the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100210:24"/>Exceſs of it both <hi>of</hi> Body and mind, of Hearts and Parts, <hi>of</hi> Veſtures, and Geſtures, in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Profeſſors, it is the <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> of the Age; its fear'd, that moſt <hi>of</hi> our Prophets mouths are judicially ſhut againſt it, and that God now ſaith of us, as formerly of <hi>Ephraim, He is joined to his Idols let him alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dread we, leaſt our Palſey Diſtempers ſhould Relax the Nerves of our Body Pollitick, or our Convulſive Cramps ſhould break them, and moſtly that the Pectant Humours in our Bodies may not abound to the raiſing up Noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Mortal Fumes and Vapours, in our Head.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Athenian Mercury</hi> may be credited, the exceſſes of our Nation in their Head Tire, hath been teſtified againſt, by Unnatural Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſſences <hi>of</hi> Bruit Creatures, but, (as its ſaid) ours by an Humane Monſtroſſity, as if the Holy GOD were more Jealous againſt us, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſeeth the Land-Defiling and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolating ſins amongſt us: what Witchrafts, and what other abominations are in the midſt <hi>of</hi> us, we have juſt cauſe both to lay ourſelves down in the Duſt, and with indignation to bear all witneſs juſtly due againſt them, and all our Pagan walking in Laſciviouſneſs, <hi>Lusts of the Fleſh, Luſts of the eyes, and Pride of Life,</hi> our exceſs of Wine, Revellings, &amp; abominable wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, by which Gods. Name is Blaſphemed among us; for which as the Lord vomited
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100210:25"/>out theſe Natives, to make room for us, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e now hath vomited us out, to make room or them; in this War he hath Ruined and Deſtroyed a whole Shire, and in a manner Depopulated a whole Province; in which De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, two Churches gathred according to Goſpel Order are extinguiſhed: One of them about Fifty years ſtanding, which was one of the firſt attacks upon us, having there been made the greateſt Slaughter, Captivity, and Plunder; the Town remaineth, but the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Candleſtick was removed: the other Church not of much leſſer ſtanding, where its ſaid, not above Four Males left of their Society, the reſt Dead, Slaughtered, or Captivated; but the Burthen of that Lamentation is, that their Faithful Paſtor, Eminent for Humility, Piety, and care of his Flock; he not being willing to leave them, was Barbarouſly Murthered in the midſt of them, his Tender and Godly. Wife Captivated, there Dyed. Oh Lord will not all this awaken us to Church Reformation, ſo as to ſet thine Altar upon its Baſis, a Sentence <hi>to be</hi> engraven upon every Church door, when we are not only under Fear <hi>of</hi> the inhabitants <hi>of</hi> this Land, but under the Deep Smarting and Killing Diſpleaſure <hi>of</hi> a Righteous, Holy, and Angry God, by theſe wicked Cannibals, who are Gods Sword, and have been ſo for many years together, and when the end will be none of our Prophets have told us: we mention not the other circumſtances relating to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100210:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; Shire; it's ſaid there have been Killed &amp; Captivated, a 1000, beſides about 140 Slain the other day: but leave it to ſuch whoſe Lot it will be to draw it up, our <hi>Pequod</hi> and <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Wars laſted about three years, whoſe Narrative is faithfully Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by two perſons of Worth, to the Honour of God, King, and Country: L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thought no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pen will hardly Undertake this.</p>
            <p>That the Great God is Departing from us, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wful Removes demonſtrate, ſhould be quite leave us, we need none to Judge between us, but our ſelves to Juſtifie him, and Condemn us; we are the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant Branches of the Noble Vine here planted, but Degenerated into that of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> whom after all Culturing to bring us unto our Priſtine Fruitfulneſs, by Impoveriſhing us, by pruning o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffour Superfluous Branches, by Loſſes at Sea, by Defeating our great <hi>Canada</hi> Deſign by Gods own Immediate Hand, Starving and Freezing to Death the Flower of our Hopeful Youth; the Lord from Heaven, and the Stars in their Courſes, Fighting againſt us; yea, Cruel Cannibals, Scalping and Fleaing of our Bodies, burning us as Sacrifices to <hi>Habamoch;</hi> but all this tends only to the killing of our Bodies; but when as the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> is Rowz'd up, and Roareth upon us, who can but fear? it exceeds brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ſtupidity, if we do not Tremble, more eſpecially, when as the Devourer out of the Bottomleſs Pit is let Looſe upon us, the Compendium of all Calamity, and the quinteſſence of Wrath, Anger, and Indignation is come upon us to the utmoſt, as if now we were to be made an Execration to God, his Holy Angels and good men, at the dreadful Claps of this tremendous Thunder, whole Fleſh is not ſhattered in pieces? How ſhould the ghaſtly ſight of the Tophet and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible World within us, and of the innate Immate
<pb facs="tcp:100210:26"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf and ſin more abominably vile, and loath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome then Hell or Devil? <hi>Who can hide from the Wrath of the Lamb?</hi> Whoſe Grace upon the Knee, in the Miniſtry of his Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Word, ſo oft hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought us and ours to be Reconciled unto him, but we would not, we have with our contempt provoked him, to deliver us up into the hand of him, who <hi>hath the Power of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let's conſider the Inſtruments Implied in this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parlative Plague, the Devil is come down againſt us, the Inhabitants of this Earth, having great Wrath, he is the Do-evil, he is the Recorded Liar, Tempter, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, and Murderer of Souls and Bodies, and what not? They are Spirits no more diſcerned by us, and as unſeen as our Souls, yet ſo near, piercing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous as the Air, Heat, or Cold, and it's only want of Divine Permiſſion, if not Commiſſion, that every one of us hath not had the experience of all this; they are Fallen Angels, Apoſtate from their Heavenly Firſt State; ſhould not this bring to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, both our Perſonal Fall in our Firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and our Relative Apoſtacy from our Church-State? Firſt Love, and Firſt Works! Our Fathers were Clothed with the Sun, the Apoſtolical Diſcipline and Doctrine were their Crown, the Moon was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Feet, but we are turned topſy turvy, Heads and Heels have changed places, a little from Heaven, was greater encouragement then a great deal from Earth, as then was the reply of a young Preacher, to one who queſtioned him, how he could be contented with ſuch poor Fare and mean Maintenance, in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mall Village; we fear that Chriſt Jeſus Indigitates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t our Churches Apoſtacy, and at our Falling from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Firſt Love.</p>
            <p>And doubtleſs God calls us, now being Alarmed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100210:26"/>by theſe Spirits, to try our particular. Eſtates, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spirit we are of? Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r of new and Heaven-born State; and alſo our Worſhip, whether it be Spiritual ſuch as he who is a Spirit, the Father of Spirits ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth; he found our Fathers ſuch of his own Making or they would not have run the risk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing themſelves, or brought us their Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Again, are we true Worſhipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs? Principled in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth of what we believe, and practice from the Word of Truth, can we give a bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r account of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church Covenant and Fellowſhip, then a B got Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt can of Maſs, or his Auricular Confeſſion, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fathers did ſo, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o did ours; it was the Cuſtome of the place they lived i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; let us min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether by theſe Helliſh Emiſſaries, God doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loudly call upon us to conſider of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Let's ponder upon the Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts or Perſons upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom this Great Wrath is fallen, they are chiefly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Members of our Churches, or their H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arers and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendants, none of the Epiſcopal, Antipedobaptiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Quakers perſwaſion, have been complained of, be Accuſers, or Accuſed, Afflicters, or Afflicted, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Devil ſetting up his Chappel ſo near to Chriſt Church, declareth his Malice, and eſpecially again us, it hath been well noted by a Miniſter of Note that the Devil now contents not himſelf to imital Jewiſh or Popiſh Modes, our he will take up the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed and Congregational Way; a ſingle Parſe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſerve his turn, but he will have Paſtor an Teacher, if he can't find a Deacon, he will not wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Widows or Deaconeſſes, his old Diaboliſm w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> not do now, to Baptiſe and give Names to the Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and her Imps, but he brings up a new Derno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iunif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> every Witch ſhall have her (ſo call'd) Spectre, attend upon her, and to be her Envoye, to Torme ſuch as they never knew or ſaw; whereas it hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100210:27"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> old ſaying,: <hi>Ignoti nulla Cupido: No Love to a perſon unknown, and conſequently as little hatred. Sauls</hi> Evil Spirit acting his Eyes to Malignity againſt <hi>David,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ympathiſed with his hand to murder him, but now between ſight and touch, a vaſt antipathy.</p>
            <p>But that which we in our ſhort Reading may make our fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh to tremble, the joynts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Knees to be looſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and our very Arfcries and Heart-ſtrings to break in lunder, at the very ſound of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; that theſe Curſed Fiends (who in the day of our Lords Humiliation, when as he deveſted his Glory, and took upon him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Form of a Servant,</hi> a Poor Carpenter (to make new, and mend old Houſes) did then beſeech him to give them leave to enter into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> parcel of Swine, and that he would not Torment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem <hi>before their time;</hi> That this Glorious and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ified Lord, <hi>Who by Death ſlew him who had the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ower of Death, that is the Devil,</hi> and upon and in is Reſurrection, <hi>made Triumph over all Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed them Captive, ſpoiling Principalities and Powers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade ſhew of them openly, after God hath highly Exalted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, even to Sit at his Right hand, and given him a Name above every Name, That in the Name of Jeſus, very knee in Heaven, Earth, and Hell ſhould bow;</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> open defiance of all this, now they ſhould inſult <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver Storm, and baſely affront the Lord of Heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth, and Hell; the Scriptures tell us, <hi>That the Devils Believe and Tremble;</hi> and this we do and muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieve: but that a Damned Crew of Devils or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itches at the Devils Table, with Red Bread and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, in deriſion of our Lords Body and Blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould ſport and feaſt themſelves (as ſome of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfeſſing Witches have ſaid, and unſaid] with that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich is their Torment and Torture, we muſt cry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and ſay, <hi>Credat Judeus Apella, Let an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100210:27"/>Jew believe it,</hi> being no Article of any Unfac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nated Chriſtians Creed: <hi>Tell not this in Gath, pubniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it not in Askelon, leſt Philiſtiahs Daughters Triumph and Rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's Hiſtoried of our Pagan Progenitors, that <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> the Great, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt of the good, and firſt of bad Popes, ſeeing ſtrange Lads of a comely Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance produced publickly to be Sold, he inquired of what Nation they were of, being told they were <hi>Angli, Engliſh,</hi> looking upon their fair faces, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid they were <hi>Angeli,</hi> Angels, and pittying them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they were Vaſſals of Satan, he took Order for the Converſion of our Nation to the Chriſtian Faith; but as for us <hi>Nov Angli, New Engliſh,</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ſmutty deformity, and Hells blackneſs, we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endred our ſelves <hi>Diaboli Veteram,</hi> Old Devils: <hi>New-England</hi> will be called, new Witch-land, <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uels</hi> Land will be Titled the Land of <hi>Abaddon; Salem Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age</hi> and <hi>Andover,</hi> will be called the <hi>Swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh Mohra</hi> and <hi>Brokula;</hi> the Country whoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Natural Small, was, as of a Field, which the Lord hath Bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, a Promenado a broad after Rain, would have Revived a mans Spirits, as ſome have experienced it; yea the whole Continent which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong after our firſt coming hither, was ſo full not only of Internals, but of External Flavour, and ſweet Odour; ſo as when Ships were divers Leagues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and had not made Land, ſo fragrant and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous was the Land to the Marriners, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey knew they were not far from the Shoar; ſuch was the plenty of ſweet Fearn, Lawrel, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ragrane Simples, this Land then abounded with; ſpecially near the Sea ſide; ſuch was the ſcent of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omatick, and Balſome bearing pines, ſpruces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Larch Trees with our Tall Cedars, exceeding all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Europe:</hi> But our ſweet ſcent is gone, we ſmell
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100210:28"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ank of Helle-bore, Henb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and poyſonful Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſock, as if we were laid out to be the <hi>American Antic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We were then honoured with <hi>Yu only have I known of all the Famities of the Earth,</hi> but what follows? <hi>therefore will I puniſh you.</hi> Priviledge doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from puniſhment, and now we are under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mart of it; we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been laid in the green bed of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yea in Ch iſt B ſome, under a Conjugal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ant, and we muſt exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e puniſhed for the breach of it; the Lord who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lous for our Fathers, he is jealous againſt us; the wilful neglect of Divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, brings under the ſame breach of the Second Command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, as the Superſtitions le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing up o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Humane Inventions, we may ſet up Croſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Surplice as lawfully as n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>glect any Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l O dinance: the grand Promiſe of Chriſt <hi>being a way wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Churches, unto the End of Ages,</hi> is conditional, and cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom that which preceedeth, nor be claimed without that which is annexed to it, <hi>viz</hi> our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that Goſpel Command, which Chriſt reſerved to take leave of his Apoſtles, and all Believers; which laſt wor'ds are or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng and ſoaking to parting Relations: <hi>Teaching them to obſerve a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l things whatſoever I have Commanded you to do, and LO I AM WITH YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>;</hi> Here is adjoyned Chriſts Note of <hi>Lo,</hi> or <hi>Behold,</hi> calling for our greateſt attention and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as well as being the remark of the higheſt truth and affirmation; and both confirmed by the <hi>Amen</hi> and laſt words of him <hi>Who is the Faithful and true Witneſs, whoſe Name is Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can it be rationally ſuppoſed? that had we not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from having Paſtors, Teachers, and Ruling Elders, and Churches doing their duty as formerly, with Family-Government kept up, that the Roaring Lion could have gained ſo much groud upon us
<pb facs="tcp:100210:28"/>(he being reſiſted would have fled) and not mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> plied ſo many Impieti s in our Towns; or ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Number of real or reputed Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es amongſt us, as it's ſaid in or about two Towns, above two hundred Accuted, one hundied Impriſoned, thirty Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and twenty Executed; yea, ſome Accuſed among our Rulers in Commonwealth and Churches, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecome places for <hi>Zim, Jm,</hi> and <hi>Ohim</hi> with the Satyrs to Dance in, On whither ſhall we go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to cover our ſhame? Shall not the ſtings of thoſe <hi>Stygian Scorpions</hi> awaken us out of our Laethal Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thergy? Are both Wiſe and Fooliſh Virgins aſleep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what need is there of Prayer? that our Eyes may be opened, and our hearts awakened, and to crie out, <hi>Awake, awake Deborah, awake, awake,</hi> is it not high time, as for every particular perſon, ſo for our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to ſearch, <hi>and try our ways, and re urn to our Firſt Husband. and the good Old Way we have walked in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The place where Satan mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his firſt aſſault, and great Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tery is to be minded: th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re he made his grand Attack where he firſt was Dethroned, and that is <hi>Salem;</hi> his preſent Rage is againſt it: its Original Name was called, <hi>Naumkek,</hi> the Boſome of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being its ſignification, as the Learned have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. It's now thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tned to be made a place and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſome of Deſolation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Turting Chriſt out of his Throne; that where Chriſts Banner had been diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there the Devil with found of Trumpet, ſets up his Enſigns, where Spiritual Songs, and Sacred Anthoms of, <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, and Peace on Earth, and good will towards men;</hi> with <hi>Amſworth,</hi> Elevated Tunes were wont to be warbled forth; that there the horrid Scriekings and Screamings of Obleſſed, Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed, and Bewitched Perſons ſhould be ſounded with ſuch hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous yellings, to the amazement of the Hearers, as if Hell and his Furies had been let looſe.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100210:29"/>
            <p>That the Noiſe of Mau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Hammers, beating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own the Carved Works in the Synagogues of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, ſhould be heard where men had been Famous, whoſe Axes had been Lifted up for hewing and ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Souls for Chriſts Spiritual Building</p>
            <p>That where the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil like Lightning had fallen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own from Heaven, before the Thundering Miniſtry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Chriſts Boanerges, there the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ack Man or Devil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould be pointed at, as vinbly ſitting or ſtanding on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Beams or Seats.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Balac</hi> and <hi>Balam</hi> Changed Stations, and Sacrifices, they could not Curſe, but muſt bleſs this People; <hi>how goodly were the Tents and Tabernacles of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Iſrael,</hi> when our Tribes according to Scriptural Order, were pitch'd about our Tabernacle, and the Ark of God in the midſt of us, when our Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Conſociations were according to Divine Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and Primitive Practice; <hi>We looked forth then as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Morning, fair as the Sun, clear as the Moon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>errible as an Army with Banners,</hi> no Inchantment or Divination againſt us, until prevailing Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion againſt Chriſts Inſtitutions were found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mong us; our Strength then was as the ſtrength of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Unicorn, the ſhout of our King was among us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tting upon his Throne of Majeſty, with the <hi>Rainbow</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout his head, ſurrounded with the four living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures, and <hi>Twenty Four E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dere, proſtrating, and throwing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Crowns before his Throne;</hi> a Lively Emblem and Character of the firſt Apoſtolical Churches Organiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and Compleated according to Chriſts Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, with the Couragious Lion like Ruling Elder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Laborious Ox-like Paſtor, the humanely Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nate Deacon, and the Eagle Eyed Teacher. Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his exceeding Immoralities, are dipp'd in the Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n Tincture of Rebellion; no marvel if our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent be ſo great, <hi>yet abundantly leſs then our Iniquities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100210:29"/>
            <p>The dread of Divine Anger and Wrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the Guilt of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſcience, which the Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of Truth declares and dictates unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as unknown in its power, and that accordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Gods Fear, ſuch is his wrath; this the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom of our Antients (when <hi>Paynimes</hi>) R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſented by <hi>Alecto,</hi> and her two Siſter-Furi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſent out of <hi>Tartaras,</hi> with their Platted <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>velures,</hi> and Contorted <hi>Locks</hi> of Hiſſing Serpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Stinging Adders, Hanging below thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Necks, whoſe Tails, Tongues, and Teeth we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> full <hi>of Deadly Poyſon,</hi> enough to Fright a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Man out of his Wits, and our Gallan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of their Head Gear: It's ſaid to be ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, that no <hi>Rattle Snake</hi> ever was ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beyond <hi>Merrimak</hi> River, the <hi>Boundary</hi> of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Firſt Patent; nor that there hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Convicted Witch on the other ſide of <hi>Piſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taquay</hi> River; but if ſome Creatures may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Credited, how do we on this Side abound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> how do the <hi>Ignatian Loyaliſts</hi> with their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Proſelytes,</hi> Triumph over our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, ſaying, <hi>We are the true Chriſtians, you the falſe, we no Lye, Swear, but Pray and Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe God;</hi> as indeed, at the Late Surpriſe of <hi>York</hi> before they fell to Sharing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their Plunder they met and Sung, <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> their Praiſes to God; and at their <hi>Veſpers,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nocturnal</hi> Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings to Smoak it, they Sing even <hi>Songs and Mattens,</hi> in the Morning in their own <hi>Language,</hi> with Harmonious Melody, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Captives Teſtify; how doth this Reflec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100210:30"/>upon the Thouſands of <hi>Non-Praying,</hi> and <hi>Non-Praiſing Familys</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> they tell us, <hi>Their Prieſts are good Men, our Ministers are Devils, and hung for Witches;</hi> What will ſome of our own Nation reproach us with? what is become of the <hi>New-Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New-Earth,</hi> of your Non parralleld Reformation you boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of? whatever Piety your Fathers preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>Pia Mater</hi> of their Brains, to be ſure it is Ardled into impious matter of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſm, in their Childrens crack'd Crowns; and therefore you are ſent into a Region, where there is <hi>Hellebore</hi> enough, for all the Mazed <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> thus is the Name of GOD, His Tabernacle, and thoſe which dwell in Heaven, Blaſphemed for our ſakes; we not giving him the Glory and Honour due unto his Name; others do ſay, and they do very ill in their ſo ſpeaking, what is become of your reſolved Revolution, which God is now Plagueing you for? and the Complicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Lies, made to encourage and further it; <hi>which of your Deſigns have proſpered ſince?</hi> Had you waited Gods time, you ſhould have had it with a Bleſſing, but by your Lyes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve deeply paid for it.</p>
            <p>Finally, that which may call for our <hi>Higgaion Selah,</hi> and deep <hi>Humiliation,</hi> is the conſideration of the time, when as <hi>Hells Hurricano</hi> ſeas'd us, when after weary waiting, in our languiſhing, and bleeding condition <hi>above a Time, Times, and half a Time;</hi> at length we were brought to Gods
<pb facs="tcp:100210:30"/>Foot, our wounds not being healed, tho ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Petitions were not granted, yet our prayers were heard, as appeareth by their Majeſties grant of a <hi>Province Charter,</hi> there declared, and here with great acclamation Proclaimed; this ve look'd at as a happy Omen of Haloyon-dayes now come to this diſtreſſed, &amp; wounded people, in this Junctor of time, or about the laying the Foundation of this ſtructure, that the great <hi>Palmony,</hi> the wonderful numberer of times, who weighs the leaſt minute of humane acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, in the exact ballance of an eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, even to the pacing of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Horſes in his Chariot, that they muſt not go faſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> flower, then to reach the very ſpot, where the Dogs had lick'd up <hi>Naboths</hi> Blood, there to lick up <hi>Ahabs;</hi> that then this <hi>Euroclydon</hi> ſhould be raiſed, to the Toral Ruine of the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fabrick; that when according to Gods graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Promiſe unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, the Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion unto us was, <hi>That our Nobles ſhould be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelves, and that our Governour ſhould procee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the midst of us, and that God would mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to draw nigh unto him, and that he di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> approach unto him:</hi> That then Hells rage di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeize us, to the breaking us in peices, if S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Stratagem had taken effect, according t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the waſting Progreſs made, that when as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hoped, God ſhould have been ours, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Childrens God as aforetime, and our Congr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations eſtabliſhed for ever; that then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould render ourſelves, or be rendred by othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100210:31"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Sons of the Sorcereſs, and Children of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Adultereſs: what high ſongs of praiſe do we owe unto <hi>Sions</hi> God, for the diſcovering of <hi>Apollions</hi> Wiles, Depths and Deceits; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or Spiriting one of the Tribe of <hi>Zebulon,</hi> rais'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p from among us, by finding out the Treaſures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id in the Sands, which hath highly tended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the raiſing of him to Honour, and the enrichment of himſelf, and Nation; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng Divinely deſtinated, &amp; humanely Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nated to be the Pilot and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eerſ man of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oor Bemiſted, and Befogg'd Veſſel, in the <hi>Mare Mortuum,</hi> and <hi>Mortiferous</hi> Sea of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raft, and Faſcination; by Heavens Conduct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccording to the integrity of his heart, not truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the Helm in any other Hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e being by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od and their Majeſties beſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed therewith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſo happily ſhaped, and ſteadily ſtee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourſe, as ſhe eſcaped Shipw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the <hi>Stygian Scilla,</hi> or the <hi>Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rontal Charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is,</hi> and now is ſafely Moa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in the <hi>Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que</hi> Sea, and under the Cape of <hi>Bone Eſperance;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e being alſo by the ſame Hand appointed, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e this Peoples Chieftain; by the Prudence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s hands, and ſtrengthned by the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ms of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mighty God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> managed the ſharp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo Edged Sword, to him committed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mparably excelling that of the Great <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>der,</hi> to the Cutting in ſunder of the <hi>Circean</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot of Inchantment, abundantly more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lt to be diſſolved, then the Famous <hi>Gordian</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Old: he being alſo led by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100210:31"/>of Our Bleſſed Gods-Spell and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſure Word of Propheſy, infinitely ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſing the Famous Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and Clue of <hi>Ariadn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath extricated us out of the Winding an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Crooked Laby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inth of Hells <hi>Meander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all be improved to the high Honour of him, who had he not been on our Side, <hi>Now may</hi> New England <hi>ſay, Had he not been on our ſide, when not only men, but Devils roſe up againſt us, we had been ſwallowed up quick, the proud Waves had gone over our Souls; Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord who gave us not up to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prey unto their Teeth, let our hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be in the Name of the Lord, who hath made Heaven, Earth, and Hell</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that now this token for good, may be improved to the quickening of us, to breaking off the Covenant made with Death, that it may be diſanulled, and our Agreement with H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, that it may not ſtand; and to make ſure our Intereſt in the firm, ſure, precious and tried Foundation, and Corner Stone, which with a <hi>Behold of Attention and Admiration,</hi> God hath <hi>Laid in Sion:</hi> Let this preventing Mercy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage poor Starv'd Prodigals, to return to their Fathers Houſe, acknowledging our ſelves unworthy to be his Sons; no, not his Maenial Servants. Own we our ſelves to be Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> wambl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng upon the Stomach or our Bleſſed Lord, and no place fitter to eaſe himſelf of us, then by ſpuing us into Hell, as was ſaid of <hi>Caparnaum;</hi> we are as ignorant, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100210:32"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ogant, we are Rich, want for nothing, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow not our Poverty, Blindneſs, or Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs; we truſt and boaſt our ſelves in lying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords, of the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> and that we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt's Non-ſuch Garden, for him to Walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Recreate himſelf in: But alas! we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either hot nor cold, a parcel of Mung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nterpendants; we are not of the Epiſcopal Form, we allow no Superiority in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes, nor Officers; where there is but one Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icer, there cannot be Preference nor Diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; and how many of our Churches have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nore? We are not Presbyterians, for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eclared Diſcipline, and their practice is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingly; they have one Paſtor, and two Ruling Elders, in their leaſt Congregations; and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Flock increaſeth, ſo they multiply their Officers; but we on the contrary; when a Churches Foundation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath been laid, they had not the Number of Forty Members in their Body; they ſolemnly then engaged, with hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifted up to Heaven, not to be without two Teaching, and two Ruling Elders, and for a while they publickly practiſed, chuſing two Ruling Elders, Ordained a Paſtor and Ruling Elder, and ſent the other to bring over a Teacher, which was done; but when they are now multiplied vaſtly above the Number, more then at firſt, they content themſelves with one Teaching, and never a Ruling Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; when as there are, as it's ſaid, above two thouſand Souls under Church Watch, &amp; none
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100210:32"/>Officially to Rule and Watch over them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not this <hi>Taking Gods Name in vain;</hi> and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Congregational Way, we Nominally pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſs it; but if we Read the Plat-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orm of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church Diſcipline, or the way of the Congr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gational Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſee how much we are varyed from it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gone back from the way, our Fathers and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves have been inſtructed in, and have recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed upon the Divine Authority of the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Word, and formerly walked accordingly.</p>
            <p>Let's not halt between two Opinions, if o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fathers Ways were Scriptural, let us practical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Juſtify them, if they be not, let us be Humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Reform; we pray that the Lord wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lead and keep us in his Truth, and reſtore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Walk in Chriſt, as we have received him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though our Ruſt is ſo inveterately Cankere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as no ſcowring will fetch it out; let's Beg th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Refiners Fire, which the Lord is purgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> with, may effectually melt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> down, that we may be fitted as Veſſels of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, <hi>Sanctified and Prepared unto every go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Work, and made fit for our Masters Uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Let this ſtimulate us to hearken unto what t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spirit ſaith unto the Churches,</hi> not advanci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mens Polliticks, before Gods Inſtitutes, nor H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane Prudentials, before Chriſt's Credentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> take we heed of diſguſt againſt Scripture Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, and plainneſs; and ſee that the true Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and Diſcipline received from our Godly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Holy Fathers, may be handed down to us, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100210:33"/>to our Children, bringing forth practical Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lineſs, whereby as they Juſtified their Profeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, ſo we may in our Lives and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make evident, the Holineſs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, of our and their Heavenly Father; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion and the true Ways of God in Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Worſhip and Diſcipline, may not evaporate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Form, <hi>without the Power of Godlineſs,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be Buried in our Predeceſſors Graves, but that it may in the midſt of years Revive, to that which was <hi>New Englands</hi> Glory: In our firſt times no complaint of Churches being it compleat of Officers, nor for want of Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tenance for them, nor for want of Materials to chooſe Officers fit to Rule: ſome have obſerved this Failure hath been upon private Brethrens Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, a diſcouragement of Diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, unleſs it were ſuch, as they had from the Preſs or Pulpit; Doth it not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the Churches King and Law giver? who both received and gave gifts to men, that the Lord God might dwell among them, yea, among the Rebellious: Shall our Churches lie under the Curſe of Barren Wombs and Dry Breaſts? Is <hi>Bethel</hi> Barren, and <hi>Athens</hi> Fruitful? Shall <hi>Cambridge</hi> the School of our Young Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets be pregnant, and an <hi>Alma Mater, a Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Mother with her Breaſts, exuberating with Radiant Beams, and Sacred Streams, to the making glad the City of our God;</hi> in ſending forth ſuch as are Accompliſhed with exquiſite and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Talents, to fit them to the Miniſterial Work
<pb facs="tcp:100210:33"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:100210:34"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:100210:34"/>of Chriſt's Holy Temple. And ſhall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Churches, which ſhould be <hi>Sion Colledges?</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Mothers of old and young Diſciples no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be ſterile? Neither capable to bring fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nurſe, or Educate any, which may be fit f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Rule in them; ſhall they be capable of no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Name, but of the Layty or this Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which was impoſed upon them, by ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Arrogated to themſelves the Title of the Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, or of being Gods Lot.</p>
            <p>Our King is blameleſs, but how much o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Churches are blame-worthy, the Lord give u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to conſider; for Brethren of low degree, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſay they know not the way of the Lord, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are of mean Eſtates, and low Capacities, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Counſel will not meet with acceptance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſome others might do; go to the Brethren o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> high degree, they know the way of the Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, but they caſt off the Yok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Lord; their occaſions will not bear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> admit of ſo mean an Employ as to be a Ruling Elder.</p>
            <p>It's Recorded to the high Honour of the <hi>French</hi> Reformed Churches, that not many years ſince, at a National Synod held at <hi>Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> very nigh unto <hi>Paris,</hi> the Metropolis of that Nation; in the ſight of all the <hi>French</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and Gallantry, there appeared twelve or ſixteen Barons, Lords, and Eſquires, who E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed not themſelves debaſed, to appear as Members of that Synodical Society, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were all of them Ruling Elders of their
<pb facs="tcp:100210:35"/>ſpective Congregations, and truly the Glory Chriſt in his Churches: This is aſſerted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Synodicon <hi>Galliae Reformatae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May we not fear that we render our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ghly Criminal againſt the Prerogative of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of Kings, and Lord of Lords; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des what is recorded in the Scripture of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, that when he took leave of his Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t his Aſcenſion, What he then gave in Charge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them; he afterward doubled the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the great and laſt Apoſtle of the Gentile Churches; inſtructing <hi>Timothy</hi> in Chriſt's Name, how he ſhould behave himſelf in the Church, and Houſe of God; he doth upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he higheſt adjuration which can be mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, Enjoyn him, as he will anſwer it <hi>before God, before Jeſus Chriſt, and the Elect Angels, that he ſhould obſerve thoſe things;</hi> namely, the Canons he had before appointed about Church Order and Officers; that he ſhould mind thoſe things, <hi>without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiallity;</hi> there muſt be no partial dealing, no preferment of one Commandment of Chriſt before another, Deacons muſt not be kept in place, with rejection of the Elders that Ruled well, nor others debarr'd of their double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſpecially thoſe who laboured in the Word and Doctrine; and the Holy All-wiſe God knowing that the Churches would Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, and that Antichriſt whoſe Myſtery of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity then wrought, would in ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner run encounter to Scripture Purity, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100210:35"/>pollute the Sanctuary Streams of Church O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinances and Officers, eſpecially Ruling Elde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> becauſe of their pragmaticalneſs with the Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Elders, about Church Rule, he jumble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and made one Officer of Teaching and Rulin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Elders, prudentially to av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id Seiſm, and calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hem both Presbyters or Prieſts; mean whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he courted and carreſſed the Deacons who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he diſtinguiſhed; ſome he called Sub-Deacon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to attend the Veſtry, to help on the Surplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly Garments of the Prieſts or Presbyters others he advanced to hear Auricular Confeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and ſay Maſs; but prudently conſiderin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Care and Truſt of the Church Stoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Treaſury was committed unto them; e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was augmented with that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Gift, concerning which, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry tells us of a voice heard in the Heavens <hi>Hodie venerum effunditur, &amp;c. This day poyſon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> powred into the Churches:</hi> That <hi>Man of Sin</hi> fore ſeeing how uſeful Deacons might be to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Clergy, he advanced the Graveſt of them to be Arch Deacons, and to be of the number o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cardinals,</hi> ſo called, becauſe they are the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines</hi> Hooks or Hindges that the Scarlet Whore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chair or Seat hangs on: This curſed Conclave are the only Elected and Electors of the Pope; their work on High Feſtivals is to Veſt their <hi>Pontifex Maximus</hi> in his <hi>Pontificalibus</hi> of Purple and Scarlet, decked with Jewels and Gold, vaſtly exceeding all Imperial State; and the Splendor of <hi>Jaddu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:100210:36"/>to <hi>Alenander,</hi> to confirm him in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt of the World. Whilſt at the High Altar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is Offering up the Blaſphemous Sacrifice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſe Arch-Deacons attend upon him, as other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eacons at the Lords Supper. Let the Candid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eader paſs by this digreſſion, deſigned to ſhew what a fine Thred this <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt ſpun; but now the Son of Perdition Sits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s God in the Temple of God, <hi>whom Chriſt will destroy with the Brightneſs of his Coming. &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt renews and doubleth the ſame Charge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the ſame Epiſtle, as it were Adjuring and Conjuring <hi>Timothy,</hi> and in him all the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, <hi>In the ſight of God, as they look to anſwer it, at that Great Day, and before Jeſus Chriſt, who made a good Confeſſion before</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>that they keep his Commandment without ſpot, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebukable, until the Appearing of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> How ſhould all theſe Obteſtations and Injunct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions make all <hi>New-England</hi> Church-Members and Officers dreadfully to quake and tremble, under the conſideration of what Guilt we lay under, by breach of this Command.</p>
            <p>Moreover the King of Saints, and Lord of Heaven and Earth, having Magnified and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted this People above any in the lower world; with <hi>Charter</hi> Priviledge to im-body themſelves into Spiritual Corporations, founded upon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitutions, and directed by Scriptural Regulations; by which Charter of Right, they are Impowred to Aſſemble and Incorporate themſelves, to Chuſe and Appoint their own
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100210:36"/>Officers, acting the whole in his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jeſties Name, and Solely by his Authority, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agreeing together, he hath paſs'd under th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great Seal of Heaven, and given his Royal Parol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Oath, and Amen, to bind or looſe in heaven whatſoever they ſhall bind or looſe on earth the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven are give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to this Church, Confeſſing and Profeſſing Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be the Son of the living God: the gates o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hell ſhall not prevail againſt it: yea, he whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name is I AM, is in the Midſt of two or three aſſembled in his Name &amp; Authority; but if they by their factions, or fractions, cannot agree, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thro their ſullen wilfulneſs, do <hi>Nonuſer, Deſuſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Refuſer</hi> any of theſe Sacred Statutes, which they by Scripture <hi>Charter</hi> are oblidg'd to act by, they forfeit their Franchiſe, &amp; may expect a <hi>Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Quo-warrant,</hi> to be ſued out by their King a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt them, WHO REQUIRED THIS AT YOUR HANDS? THIS IS NOT THE FEAST, FAST OR DUTY THE LORD REQUIRES. By not obſerving all things he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Commanded, they forfeit the challenge of his promiſed Preſence with them, if they refuſe any Officer, which he hath inſtated in the Churches, they expoſe themſelves to the Forfeiture of the ſaid Charter.</p>
            <p>And he who knoweth not, what a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Superſtitions was by this door of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, let into the firſt Churches, he is not ſo vers'd in divine and humane Church Hiſtory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the time of the fulfilling Propheſy we are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100210:37"/>caſt into, calls for: our crying out, <hi>The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord,</hi> will not free us from being Diſchurched, more then <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was; ſhe was ſeat to <hi>Shilo. N. England</hi> needs not to Travel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aſia</hi> to learn it; every poor <hi>French Refugee,</hi> who hath ſet his Foot in <hi>N. England,</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it unto us, whoſe Churches have yielded more Faithful Martyrs, then all the other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in <hi>Europe;</hi> their care of Supplying the Poor Churches, out of the Large Treaſury, and by the Liberality of the Richer, was Exemplary; and the Providing Maintenance to the Widows, and Orphans of their Deceaſed Paſtors, was Preſidential; it was the ſpecial Work of their National Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, and doth condemn us; Chriſt that knows their Charity, Service, Faith, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience after their Re reformation, will make this <hi>Thyatiras laſt works to be more than her first.</hi> Oh that we might apply our Hearts to theſe things, that they may ſink into our Souls! Kings out of their Natural Clemency, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate from the Severity of Law, but if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt be added, it aggravates the Offence; Our caſe is ſuch as only Soveraign Grace can Cure; God hath oft wrought for his Names Sake, Let us Plead it with him, <hi>Lord we are call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by thy Name, Leave us not, Let us not be abhorr'd for thy Names Sake; Let not the Throne of Thy Glory, be further Diſgraced, before Popiſh and Pagan Adverſaries?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's ſaid that none but Parliaments Laxneſs
<pb facs="tcp:100210:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o maintain their juſt and legal Proprietie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> undo the Body Polittck of a Nation; ſo no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can undo our Spiritual Corporations, but their Members; giving up their due juſt Church Power and Priviledge, into the bands of ſome <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> as befel the Primitive Churches.</p>
            <p>As we began with a caution from our great <hi>Cotton,</hi> ſo we ſhall draw to a concluſion with the Animadverſion of the great Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Champion, Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who in the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of theſe Churches from Sciſm, cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g'd upon them by Dr: <hi>Stilling sfleet;</hi> the ſaid Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Man, who there, and in his other Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Works upon that Subject, doth but Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe and Comment upon the Book of Mr. <hi>Cottens Keys,</hi> as he himſelf hath publiſhed to the World; in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cawdry,</hi> That upon ſearch of the Scriptures, and weight of Argument thence deduced, finding the Work of the <hi>Keyes</hi> exactly anſwering <hi>the Wards of the Lock of Christs Kingdom;</hi> he was proſelited from the Claſſical, unto the Congregational Way of Churches. Let it with all ſubmiſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be conſidered, whether its Rumination may not be our concern, who Writing of the State of theſe Churches ſaith: <hi>That when a People through an apprehenſion of their own ignorance, weakneſs, and unmeetneſs (well if it be not La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zineſs and Idleneſs) to diſcern and judge matters of Religion for themſelves; and their own duty be kept and debar'd from it, or when through their own ſloth, negligence and vitiouſneſs, ſhall be really
<pb facs="tcp:100210:38"/>uncapable to manage their own intereſt in Church Affairs, as fit only to be governed, if not as Bruit Creatures, yet as mute perſons; theſe things ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mplyed by the ambition of the Clergy, ingroſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll things in the Church, to themſelves, as they did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n former Ages: That if the old Popedom do not Return, a new one wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be Erected as bad as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> God forbid this prognoſtick ſhould be the Fate of our Churches; yet when we read the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> advice to <hi>Coloſſe, Say to Archippus, Take heed to thy Miniſtry, which thou haſt Received of the Lord;</hi> when we conſider the neglect of it, we know not what to ſay.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Learned Man, in a Book Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince his Death, concerning the Rule and Order of Congregational Churches, which he aſſerts to be the only Apoſtolical Churches, both according to the Rules of Scripture, and according to the Example of Primitive Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Antiquitie, to whom next unto the Sacred Scriptures, we owe greateſt Veneration and Credence, which he in the ſaid Book ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, in that Diſcourſe, treating of the Ruling Elders Office and Duty, he ſaith, <hi>I admire that any man ſhould have ſo much confidence in his own Abilities, ſo as to ſuppoſe himſelf Meet, and Able, for the Diſcharge of both ſorts of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ders in the least Church of Chriſt;</hi> In the ſame Treatiſe, he further affirms, <hi>Its evident, that neither the Purity, Order, nor the Beauty, or Glory of the Churches of Chriſt, nor his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or Authority in the Government of them,
<pb facs="tcp:100210:38"/>can be long preſerved without the multiplication Elders in them, according to the proportion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Number of their reſpective Members; for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereof, the Churches of old, and late, have De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated into Anarcby, or Confuſion, or elſe gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> themſel vss up, unto the dominion of ſome prelati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Teachers to rule at pleaſure, which was the poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and bane of the other Primitive Churches; and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will do the ſame for the future, in the neglect this Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God avert theſe ſad Omens, that they ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> befal our Churches; and yet when w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read how the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> wrought app<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in ſome who loved the preheminence even in the Apoſtles time, we are at a loſs, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humbly leave it with him, whoſe Face is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be ſeen, but his back parts only, while he paſſing before us in his Glory, and taking way his hand.</p>
            <p>Hath not <hi>New-England</hi> experienced this grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth, What is become of the Majeſty, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Glory of Chriſts Appearing in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Churches, unto which Chriſts Defence is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed when we were compleated according t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rule, as at the firſt: Let's take Chriſts Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, to <hi>Remember from whence we are Fallen, &amp; Repent;</hi> Remember our Rulers which hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> declared unto us the Word of God, whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fatth follow, conſidering what hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the end of their Converſation; <hi>Jeſus Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever.</hi> Let's no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be carried about with divers Doctrines, and
<pb facs="tcp:100210:39"/>to mind what Mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orton</hi> hath left us to chew upon.</p>
            <p>In his Treatiſe call'd, <hi>The Heart of</hi> New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, <hi>rent at the Blaſphemies of the Times,</hi> whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords are: <hi>It concerneth</hi> New-England <hi>always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> remember, that originally they are a</hi> PLANTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ION <hi>Religious, not a</hi> PLANTATION <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rade; the Profeſſion of the Purity of Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, is written upon their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead;</hi> a ſpot of this vaſt <hi>Jeſhimon</hi> converted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Corn-fields, Orchards, Streets Inhabited, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a place of Merchandiſe cannot denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate <hi>New-England,</hi> all theſe notwithſtanding if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e fall away from her Profeſſion, call her <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>habod, The Glory is Departed;</hi> in ſuch a caſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat was ſaid of <hi>Samnium,</hi> ſometimes a Fa-, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous City in <hi>Italy, viz.</hi> That they could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd SAMNIUM in SAMNIUM, will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied in theſe Churches; <hi>vix.</hi> That NEW-ENGLAND is not to be found in NEW-EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GLAND, nor BOSTON in BOSTON. God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orbid, that after <hi>New England</hi> hath now ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Twenty Years and more, like a Light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Hill, it ſhould at laſt go out in the ſnuff of <hi>Morelianiſm;</hi> thus far the words of <hi>Boſtons</hi> great and ſecond Seraphical Teacher, who For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Years ſince, declared theſe Fears about us; as will further appear in the laſt page of this Scribled Narrative, in his Funeral Elegy upon Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> Death. When our Stocks and Farms were not ſo multiplied, nor our Trade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Merchandiſe ſo increaſed, nor the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100210:39"/>of our Members, nor Mortuaries, ſo grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as now. As Holy <hi>Herbert</hi> in his Pious Poem foretold of us.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>As Gold and Grace never yet did agree,</l>
               <l>Religion alway ſiding with Poverty.</l>
               <l>That as the Church ſhall thither <hi>Weſtward</hi> flie,</l>
               <l>So Sin ſhall Trace and Dog her inſtantly.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Yet we could maintain our Officers. No queſtion was then about the Miniſters Table<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how they ſhould be ſupplied; the Silver and Gold in <hi>Darius,</hi> his Exchequer was the Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and he brought it out to advance Temple-work; if the Church Stock needed Enlargement, a word then from the Deacons was ſufficient to bring forth more then enough, yea to <hi>Moſes</hi> calling for a reſtraint; ſuch inlargedneſs of heart then appeared, as ſome old Planters may Remember.</p>
            <p>It was an awful Speech of a Worthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel lately utter'd upon a Falt-Day in a Neighbour Congregation; that he feared the Churches did not underſtand the Cauſe of Gods preſent Controverſy; that it was Reformation God looked for, who us'd this Motive to provoke to Duty; that if the preſent Generation did not attend and do their Duty, the next ſhould not, and would not be capable of it; and indeed how can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, That they ſhould Reform that which they know not to be an evil, nor to fall upon practice of an unknown Precept; Paſtors and
<pb facs="tcp:100210:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Teachers are accounted as Supernumeraries; no Rule but for one Officer in a Church; and as for Ruling Elders, they have been taken up by Tradition; that there is but one word in the whole Bible for them; yet the Faith once given to the Sains, is earneſtly (yet Regularly) to be contended for by them; but they will find them more then twice mentioned, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. among Church Officers, <hi>viz. The Teacher is to attend on Teaching, the Paſtor or Exhorter, on Exhortation; the Giver, to do it with ſimplicity; He that Ruleth, with diligence:</hi> can there be a fuller deſcription of the Ruling Flders Office and Work, then here is declared, &amp; alſo in the Plat-form of Church Diſcipline. It's therefore no Humane Invention, nor Apochriphal Practice of our Predeceſſors: It's Remembred by ſome of the Old Planters Children, that there were ſuch men, when they were young, that were called Ruling Elders; but what men they were, or what was their work, they profeſſed they could not tell: What a ſhame is it to our Churches, that through <hi>Diſuſe, Miſuſe</hi> and <hi>Nonuſe</hi> of them, ſuch a queſtion ſhould be put by any of above Fifty Years of Age, now Living among us; all which is affirmed for a certain known Truth.</p>
            <p>The ſame Reverend man of God, being imployed the laſt <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Wars, by our Worthy Elders, to make Report and Return to the General Court, of the provoking evils then found among us, did repreſent to them, the Churches incompleatneſs of Officers, to be
<pb facs="tcp:100210:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>one of the great evils, Provocations, &amp; grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Diſpleaſure unto God, then among us, ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> replied unto him, <hi>That the country and Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were poor, and could not maintain them;</hi> he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them a Ready, Grave, and Divine Anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>True,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>were they mens Officers;</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were argument in what they ſaid, but bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> GODS Officers, there was no ground for fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of it; he having Promiſed and ſaid, <hi>Prove a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try me;</hi> if we could but truſt him, he wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> open the Heavens, and pour down his Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: it's Robbing of God we are now call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to an account for, we fear that Covetuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Pride, and Ambition, hinders the Diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of our <hi>Achan,</hi> The Lord pour down u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Jeruſalem, the Spirit of Grace, and Suppli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cation, and that he would open the Fountain y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sin and Uncleanneſs; that Holineſs unto the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> may be writ upon our hearts, houſes, and empl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, whether Sacred or civil and upon our</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>teritys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As we have cauſe to weep over and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wail our former tears, begging that they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb, ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe our faint Sighs and Sobs may be Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, and accepted in the Blood of the eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, that what we ſay, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> realized in our Souls. The good Lord dire our Hearts into the knowledge of his love waiting for the Pouring forth of his Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on ourſelves, and the riſing generation, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:100210:41"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cern, and by the Divine Aids there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, be enabled, to do the reſpective work of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r Generation, according to the will of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OD, before theſe things be hid from our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yes.</p>
            <p>That we may have the taſts of that Mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Grace, ſpringing from the Love of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther, who knows the thoughts of his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>art, and manifeſts them to poor Penitents, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they paſſing through the heart of him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ho layeth in the Fathers Boſome, may deſcend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to our hearts, by the Holy Spirit dwelling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us, which Bleſſed Circulation Reverting by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Operation of the ſame Spirit which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th requeſts for us, who know not to pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we ought, and paſſing thro' the heart, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nds of our great Mediator, may arrive, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cend into the heart of the Father, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Origine and Fountain of all Bleſſedneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Father himſelf loving us.)</p>
            <p>That this Spirit may make interceſſion for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Groans, which can't be uttered, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at ſearches the hearts, knowing what is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd of the Spirit, becauſe he maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſion for the Saints according to the Will of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d; Oh that we might experience theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ngs, that this Heavenly Dove ſent into our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arts, may make us grean, and mourn, like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe in the <hi>Clefts of the Rocks,</hi> that as the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eation growns, and travails in pain, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cks ſtretched out, waiting to be delivered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m their Bondage and Corruption, into the
<pb facs="tcp:100210:41"/>Liberty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Sons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God; that we receivin the firſt fruits thereof, may with Eyes an Hands lifted up, wait for the Adoption, eve the Redemption of our Souls and Bodies which Great Grace, the GOD OF AL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> GRACE, Grant to Us, and Our Poor Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with all his ISRAEL; <hi>For the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Our Dear LORD JESUS, to who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the FATHER, and HOLYSPIRI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Be the Kingdom, Power, and Glory, For Ever</hi> AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>A FUNERAL ELEGY, Upon the Death of the truly Reverend Mr. JOHN COTTON.</head>
            <head type="sub">Late Teacher of a Church of Chriſt at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England:</hi> Who Died the Twenty Third, was Buried the Twenty Ninth of <hi>December.</hi> 1652.</head>
            <l>ANd after <hi>Winthrop, Hooker, Shepheards</hi> Herſe,</l>
            <l>Doth <hi>Cottons</hi> Death call for a Mourning Verſe.</l>
            <l>Thy Will be done, yet Lord who dealeth thus,</l>
            <l>Make this great Death expedient for us.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Luther</hi> pull'd down the Pope, <hi>Calvin</hi> the Prelate ſlew,</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Calvins</hi> Lapſe, chief Cure to <hi>Cottons due.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Cotton</hi> whoſe Learning, Temper, Godlineſs,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Germane</hi> Phaenix lively did expreſs.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Melancthon's</hi> all, may <hi>Luther's</hi> word but paſs</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Melancthon</hi>'s all, in our Great <hi>Cotton</hi> was.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>Whilſt he was here, Life was more Life to me,</l>
            <l>Now he is not, Death hence leſs Death to me.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>That Comets great mens death do oft forego,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>This preſent Comet doth too ſadly ſhow,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>This Prophet's dead, yet muſt in's Doctrine ſpeak,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>This Comet ſaith, elſe muſt New-England break.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>That e're it be, the Heav'ns avert it far,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>That Meteors ſhould ſucceed our greateſt Star.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>Bostons</hi> Orb <hi>Winthrop</hi> and <hi>Cotton</hi> were,</l>
            <l>Theſe Lights Extinct, Dark is our Haemiſphere.</l>
            <l>In <hi>Boſton</hi> once how much ſhin'd of our Glory,</l>
            <l>VVe now Lament, Poſterity will Story.</l>
            <l>Let <hi>Boston</hi> live, who had and ſaw their VVorth.</l>
            <l>And did them hot our, both in Life and Death.</l>
            <l>To him <hi>New-England</hi> truſt in this Diſtreſs,</l>
            <l>Who will not leave his Exiles Comfortleſs.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Norton.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Reader, Be pleaſed in page 18 for <hi>Chriſtopher Gardner</hi> Read Sir <hi>Christopher Gardner.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:42"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:43"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100210:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. Lin. 11. for <hi>in Churches,</hi> read <hi>in the Churches.</hi> pag: 6. l. 18. for <hi>graceful,</hi> read <hi>grateful.</hi> p. 12. l. 30. for <hi>Tarting</hi> read <hi>Parting.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. l. 11. in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tead of <hi>Pectant,</hi> r. <hi>Pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant.</hi> p. 46. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. for <hi>Fathers,</hi> r <hi>Father.</hi> p. 48. l. 27. for <hi>Storm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Scorn.</hi> p. 49. l. 26. r. <hi>Internal.</hi> p. 50. l. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>alway.</hi> p. 69. l. 29. r. <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</hi> p. 72. l. 6. r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ints. ibid l. 8. for <hi>twice,</hi> r. <hi>once.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
